<ROOT>

    

    <record><version/><date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2014-05-15</date><date_nonpreferred_format/><cms_record_id/><title>Louise Gluck interviewed by Devin Becker</title><partial_transcript/><synopsis/><keywords/><subjects/><gps>42.371511, -71.109691</gps><gps_text>Cambridge, Massachusetts</gps_text><hyperlink/><hyperlink_text/><accession/><duration>01:52:39</duration><collection_id/><collection_name/><series_id/><series_name/><repository/><repository_url/><interviewee>Louise Gluck</interviewee><birthyear>1943</birthyear><residence>Cambridge, Massachusetts</residence><interviewer>Devin Becker</interviewer><file_name>gluck.mp3</file_name><next>strickland</next><previous>pinsky</previous><sync/><media_id/><media_url>http://www.devinbecker.org/mp3/gluck.mp3</media_url><mediafile>

        <host>Other</host>

        <host_account_id/>

        <host_player_id/>

        <host_clip_id/>

        <clip_format>audio</clip_format>

    </mediafile><language>english</language><index/><type>application/mp3</type><description/><rel/><transcript>

        [00:00:00] PART 1

DB:	If you would state your name and the location we're at for this interview.

LG:	Louise Glück, the Glück is spelled with a ü and then out loud and the name is Hungarian.  We're in Cambridge, Massachusetts in my apartment.

DB:	Of course I know the answers to many of these questions but what genres do you work in?

LG:	Poetry and I have written some essays, some forewords to books when I was judging first book prize contests, but in the main, poetry.

[00:05:00]

DB:	Yeah.  Are you going to collect those essays?

LG:	Yeah.

DB:	Good, those are so excellent.  You worked really hard at them, I know.

LG:	I worked so hard and they ruined 10 summers because they made me frantic with anxiety, the idea of trying to do... to serve a new talent and to describe its uniqueness and it's a natural offshoot of teaching, which I've loved for years.  I love everything about judging those contests and I loved working with the poets on their manuscript.  In the early days before Yale Press was convinced that this was worthwhile, I used to buy a plane ticket for people so they could come here and spend three days working.

DB:	Okay.

LG:	Then I would make very detailed recommendations, which they were free to not take because the book had won.  On the other hand, they weren't free to change the books any which way because I could say, "This is not the book I chose."  They could stay exactly as we were or they could respond to suggestions and work further.  Many of them actually felt a great need for that kind of work and they just didn't have somebody who was willing to take that kind of detailed daily interest.

DB:	From what I'm experiencing, it doesn't seem to be a very common thing for the selector to make a real interest after they choose and then they are done, and they get their money and they are on their way.

LG:	I think that's sort of how most of them feel and most of them also don't want... is this off the point that you're...?

DB:	No, it's all one thing.

LG:	Okay.  Most of them don't want to read a lot of books or in some contests, they are not permitted to.  They are sent 10 finalists screened by...

DB:	Who knows?

LG:	It varies.  But if these manuscripts are being screened by people whose aesthetic judgment you question, you don't know what you're getting.  So I asked to see as many as possible with the understanding that nothing would be thrown out until a winner was chosen because if I didn't find a winner in 100 manuscripts, I was going to see the next 100.

DB:	Right.

LG:	And that was all fun because you didn't have to read each book through to completion and you didn't have to write a little paragraph evaluating it the way you do for other kinds of things.  If you didn't love it, it was unlikely you would choose it.  You would put it in the unlikely pile, and my living room was filled with piles identifiable by me and then at the end, I would read through the piles to see whether something got promoted or demoted.  Some years were thrilling, I mean, it was too much stuff.  In those years, most of the runners up ended up winning.

DB:	Some other...?

LG:	Well, later, the Yale prizes.

DB:	Oh okay.  You encouraged them to resubmit.

LG:	Yeah.  Some people would submit like three and four times.

DB:	Yeah, that's interesting.  I want to know who it is.

LG:	Well, we would do that when that's off.

DB:	Okay.  So what time of year were you usually doing that evaluation?

LG:	It worked out very well because a lot of that time, I was just working half time at Yale, not in the spring semester, and I would get the manuscripts in December, right after the semester ended.  Sometimes, it was a little bit of... I try to give myself a couple of weeks of blank.  The cartons would start to come from the people who were screening and Yale allowed the appropriation of a mechanism that I had picked up from Michael Collier when I judged the Bakeless prize that he supervised.  He had each poet who was judging choose younger poets to screen.  So I chose 10 poets and they got paid at [inaudible 00:09:46] and each of them read 100 books and sent me 10 and kept 90.  That meant that I had someone to talk to about each of these manuscripts and sometimes...

[00:10:00]

LG:	...we would talk before they even send things and they would say that we need a few poems and say, "Well, do you want to see this?  I'm on the fence."  I had great people screening for me and they were people whose judgments I trusted and who sent me their broadly diverse manuscripts.  One thing that I wanted was a series in which the books weren't all alike and they are not.  Anyway, so that was great but it meant that all the prose writing I did for 10 years was writing forrwords.  So I have a stack and a few other essays.  It doesn't make as pleasing a collection as the first one but I can't stand the idea that it's just going to go nowhere.

DB:	No, I will be very excited to have that book.

LG:	Oh well, good.  Do you have an idea for a title?  Not three words.

DB:	Not three words?

LG:	Not like Proofs and Theories, this and that.  Not a clone.

DB:	No.

LG:	I don't either.

DB:	If I think of some options.

LG:	Please, I really need it.

DB:	Okay.

LG:	I'll acknowledge you.

DB:	Is it coming out at this...

LG:	Yeah, but not...

DB:	Not, I know.  You've got this next book.

LG:	Yeah.

DB:	Okay.  Well, that was the first question.

LG:	That was the first?  What was that about?  It wasn't about digital.

DB:	No, it was just the general.  I went to AWP this year which was terrifying.

LG:	I've never been.

DB:	Yeah, you should never go.

LG:	It's sort of what I think.

DB:	But there was a panel with Richard Siken and who were the other two?

LG:	Arda Collins?

DB:	Arda Collins and...

LG:	Fady Joudah?

DB:	Exactly and they were talking.  I caught the second half so I heard Siken talking about he is working with you on Crush, which was really funny.  He's funny.  I didn't know how funny he was.  The book is pretty intense but...

LG:	Right.  He's a great visual artist.

DB:	Okay, Oh yeah?  Does he, really?  I like that.

LG:	I think he is amazing.

DB:	Yeah.

LG:	He made these envelopes because he thought he was going to be living in Europe and so he made it.

FEMALE:	That one's wonderful.

LG:	All of these things and, you know, the message was the envelope.  I don't know how you can frame them because...

DB:	Yeah, who knows?  They are very nice.

LG:	Aren't they wonderful?

DB:	Yeah.  He has another book coming out too.

LG:	Yeah, he does, which I saw a long time ago.  I mean, the other, Peter Streckfus has a new book and, it's wonderful.

DB:	I really loved his first book.

LG:	I love that book.  I love that book and I just think he's an amazement.  Jay Hopler has a new book that he's peddling.  Those first three, I worked with really closely on the first books and with Peter and Jay, I worked a lot on the second too.  With Richard, much less, I mean, it's funny because he needed a lot of editing.  His poems were way too long and his stanzas were too long.  The lines were too long but you had to preserve that avalanche sense that had long sense and so it's very hard to figure out.  But once he saw a way of approaching the language, to edit it and still preserve its character, he was an excellent editor and he may feel that he just knows...

[00:15:00] PART 2

LG:	... how to do it on his own.  I mean, we talked on the phone and I saw early versions of a lot of the poems.

DB:	Yeah, and Crush has become a sort of its phenomenon.

LG:	Cult book.

DB:	Yeah it really has.

LG:	I know.

DB:	It's interesting.  I mean, I remember, I first heard about it at Bread Loaf that year I was there and somebody said like, "Have you read Crush?"  I was like, No, I'm sorry," and it was a bust and I taught it.  We know the MFA students kind of at Idaho and some of them are teaching it, or like the guy who was actually working for me in digital based his final poem and his thesis off those lines and that sort of stanza style.

LG:	Well, a lot of people sound like him.  You can see, they read the book and then they can't get out of it.

DB:	Yeah, that's the danger.

LG:	That's hard.

LG:	Yeah, I know.  So your primary genre is poetry, correct?  Yes.  So what kinds of devices do you have access to or use for writing?

LG:	I have access to an iPad.  I have never written anything on it except a terse email and I cannot bear reading poems in that form.  In fact today, there was a conversation with my publisher because I finally figured out a way to their satisfaction to convert their poetry listings to ebooks.  The question was would I give my permission and I cannot bear reading poems in that form - scrolling down a page, you have no idea how long the thing is, you don't know whether you're in the middle or at the end.

	Miranda, who is my, you know, daily editor not my big guy editor, who was a student of mine at Yale.  It's very funny, I have all these students now in positions of -I hesitate to say authority - but I turn to them for solace and advice all the time.  Miranda is quite great and her judgment is wonderful.  She was a wonderful beginning writer too.  Anyway, she said she thought it was a good idea.  She said for people who are used to reading in this form, it's not such a violation, but it makes me uneasy.  So if friends, for example, when I was in Stanford and friends would send me drafts or poems as we do, I do through the mail or at Stanford, I would give something to a secretary, but there wasn't a lot, well, that's further up the pike.  I just have to go to someone who can print it out.

DB:	Print it out on paper.

LG:	Yeah.  Well, I will have to be able move my pen around and make notes, first of all.  I have to see what it looks like, what the duration is, and I have to be able to read the beginning and the end.  I have to have them all in my head but mainly is that I don't know how to make notes otherwise.  But I have this that gives me fantastic pleasure in other ways.  I love it and it's an endless amusement.  I keep it very near my bed or on my bed.  If I wake in the middle of the night, I turn on the light and I see if anybody is reading to me.  I always loved getting mail and now I have that experience around the clock, except that I check it every four minutes and I'm so heartbroken when there's no change.  It's just that same old email from Amazon or some website that I patronized once.

[00:20:00]

LG:	I have a regular old fashioned cell phone.  I only got a cell phone about five years ago because I'm taxi dependent and I needed to be on the street and call the guy.  So it doesn't receive emails or anything like that.

DB:	It's a regular iPad just like the first?

LG:	No.

DB:	The larger one or the smaller one?

LG:	The iPad that I have?

DB:	Yeah.

LG:	I'll show you because how it looks is part of its story.

DB:	Okay.

LG:	I don't know what size this is.

DB:	Oh this is for you?

LG:	Yeah, the little one.  I don't know what size this is.

DB:	That's the regular size.  They have the minis now.  That's the only kind of difference, size.

LG:	What happened was, I went to - some of these have to be off the record.  This event, I was invited to this thing, the Golden Plate Award sponsored by, held by something called the Academy of Achievement.  I mean, it sounds so spurious and ridiculous, but you showed up and you got $10,000.  It was in Washington DC and the hotel was enormously swank, I mean, super swank.  So I asked my agent to find out what was the fewest number of days I could go and still collect the fee, and it was one.  So I scaled and laid back and then I found out when I arrived that the dinner the night before for the honorees had been in the Chambers of the Supreme Court with the Justices, just the Justices and the honorees.  I could've eaten dinner.  This is the part that needs to be off the record.

DB:	Okay.

LG:	The organization, it was subsequently discovered, not by me but by others whom I trust, is violently corrupt.  They fund impoverished students, helping them to go to college but then the students can't pay back the loans, and the government of course covers.  So they make money off these loans that paralyzed the people who are loaned money.  I'm not savvy about this sort of stuff.  Anyway, when I arrived, part of my welcome package was this thing and it was all programmed with the winners and their bios.  The entertainment, the last night when we all got our plates....

DB:	You've actually got gold plates?

LG:	Yeah, I mean, the room was very, very good for a banquet meal.  It was extraordinary.  In the space, I mean, if you squared off this room, this is the whole thing.  It certainly wasn't bigger.  It might have been a little smaller.  So picture an intimate space.  I always want people to guess but it's ridiculous what they are going to guess.  It was like seeing Mozart.  It was Aretha Franklin.

DB:	Really?

LG:	Aretha.  She was there right where the tulips are, different color.  So the whole thing was eerie.  Anyway, the guy gave me this when I arrived.  I said, "Don't give me this.  I'm never going to use it.  Give it to someone who can make use of it."  He said, "I have to give it to you," and I said, "But I won't use it.  I don't want it.  I'll leave it in the hotel room.  Please give it to someone else."  He said, "I have to give it to you," and he thrust it at me and then I was holding it and then I seemed to have it.  So I took it to the hotel room and I'd seen how people push the screens so I pushed the screen.  Nothing happened.  I mean, it wasn't connected to anything and I thought I apparently don't have the gift.

[00:25:00]

	So I then brought it home.  Well actually, I had somebody ship it to me and then I kept looking at it and thinking, "I guess now that I own this, I should learn how to use it."  But I lingered in that state for about six months and then at some point, I asked one of my, I have former students from Williamson Yale I'm still in touch with and the Yale students sometimes come up here to work on their stuff, and one did and I said, "What do I have to do to learn how to use this?"  He said, "Well, you need to get wifi."  I said, "How do I do that?  Do I call AT&amp;T?  Do I call Comcast?"  He said, "Call Comcast."  So I called Comcast and they asked me questions I couldn't answer.  "Do you have a blank?  Do you blank blank?"  I said, "I know nothing.  You have to just assume I have nothing."

	I thought,  "This is not going to work."  It wasn't working so I called the student back in and said, "Write me a script.  Here's the kinds of things I was asked.  Tell me what I say."  So I went back and I recited my script.  Someone came to the house and installed a device.  No one had told me that it had this little strobe flickers.  I am epileptic so I thought, "Oh, this is never going to do."  So I called the student again and he said, "You can turn it around.  Just turn it so the strobe is facing another direction."  I did but then I still didn't have an email account so then someone else came up to work on poems and I got an email.  Then I was so horrified at this transformation that I didn't do anything for another six months.

	And then Robert Pinski, I told him I had an email and he sent me a photo of one of his grandchildren.  I opened this little thing and there was a photo.  I thought, "Wow."  So I learned certain skills.  I still can't add an attachment.  No, that's not what they are called - an app.  I don't know how to add an app so somebody has to do that one when I want....

DB:	Need an app, yeah.

LG:	Yeah, like I wanted HBO because I couldn't...

DB:	HBO to go, yeah.

LG:	But then I have all of these names, passwords and I can never remember what they are.  Then they ask me, "You say you want to change your password."  Yes.  And they ask me my special secret question, which makes absolutely no sense, "What is your favorite pet's name?" and I didn't have pets, I mean, except when I was a child.  And they say, "Well, we can't change the question because the person who this is came up with this question," and I think, "How could I?"  I never would have.

DB:	Right.

LG:	I still haven't figured that out but now I try to write down the passwords.

DB:	Passwords so you have some other place to get it from.

LG:	In my phonebook because they are such a long list in my head and I don't know which one is for which.

DB:	Right.

LG:	So all that stuff I hate.

DB:	Yeah, it's such a daily part of life now.  I mean, we all dislike it and when it's new to someone, it's also, you kind of realize how awful some of it is.

LG:	I like the adventure of the mail and I like watching.  I've watched a lot of television and when I had bronchitis this winter, it was wonderful because there it was in bed with me.  I didn't have to go anywhere.  I didn't have to sit in a chair.

DB:	You've got it all right there and you had endless stuff too, right?

LG:	Yeah.

DB:	You have Netflicks or...?

LG:	Everything.

DB:	Oh okay.  You're set.

LG:	Yeah and I have another thing.  I have, I own Breaking Bad.

[00:30:00] PART 3

LG:	I didn't want to wait for the last season.

DB:	Yeah, it's worth it.  That was a pretty intense season.

LG:	Yeah.  Once Gus died up, the real spine went out of the show, in my view, but I loved it.  I loved that show.

DB:	Me too.  We just finished that one.

LG:	Oh yeah?

DB:	Not too long ago, yeah.

LG:	What else have you liked?

DB:	TV wise?  What are we watching now?

FEMALE:	The Americans.

DB:	The Americans is very good.

LG:	Is it good?

DB:	Yeah, that's a very good one.

LG:	Have you seen Friday Night Lights?

DB:	I've watched some of Friday Night Lights.  You've never seen it, right?

FEMALE:	No.

DB:	We need to do the whole thing.

LG:	You have to start from the beginning.

DB:	Yeah.  I did it several years ago.

LG:	I love that.  I watched that at Stanford this year and I thought it was going to take me five seasons.  I thought, "This is going to last me the whole of my Stanford experience.  It's going to be great," and I finished it about two weeks but then I didn't want to watch anything else.  It's like when you read a really marvelous book.  There was something about... I mean, I can record and watch things on demand but there was something about the fact that I could do this anywhere.  And if I went to a hotel, I could do it.

DB:	You still have it.  You still do what you want.

LG:	It was an amazing discovery for me and I loved that show, and I ended up watching the last season a second time.  And then I still didn't want to watch anything else so I watched the first season, and I was ready.  But I have not found a new thing.

DB:	Since then?

LG:	Since then.  Well, it has been a month.

DB:	Have you watched The Wire?

LG:	I watched The Wire on TV at Frank's house.

DB:	Yeah, that would be a nice...

LG:	Because he has equipment.  He has lab quality equipment.

DB:	Well, I'll think of some other ones.

LG:	Okay.

DB:	Yeah, we should talk about it.

LG:	Yeah, if you think about it...all right, yeah.

DB:	I'll let you know.  You watch a lot of TV.

LG:	Okay.  I want a title for my book and recommendations.

DB:	Okay.

LG:	All right, moving along.  So far this is a tad of an interview, isn't it?  We haven't had any technical discussion.

DB:	No, it's good though.  It's good.  It's about being a person.  I've got to kind of adjust on the flag here but I think I'll just skip these because you don't really, you don't write any poems on iPad.  You never have them in digital format until they go to your publisher essentially and then they will.... Do you know how they do it?

LG:	I send them a typed script.

DB:	You send them typed script and then they...

LG:	Which is kind of harrowing because then I have to proof the digital and be sure there haven't been mistakes, and there are always huge mistakes.  I could pay somebody to do it but it would still be the same problem of having to proof it.  I imagine that I'm stuck with that for life because I cannot imagine typing poems on that board.

DB:	So when you send it to FSG and then someone types like... or do they scan it and then, I mean, do you know how they do it?

LG:	No.

DB:	Okay because I mean, in your ways they should be able to...

LG:	But I can tell you who would know if you want to ask.

DB:	Yeah.

LG:	Do you want?

DB:	Maybe, I don't know.

LG:	All right.

DB:	I'm just interested, I mean, but once they do that, then they send it back to you and you make sure that everything is right.  I mean, you go back and forth with them with the proofs for quite a bit, right?

LG:	Yeah, right.

DB:	I remember when I was a student.  I think you had, would it have been Vita Nova or Seven Ages you were working on?

LG:	I don't know.

DB:	And you were telling me how you were reading it backwards.

LG:	Oh yeah.  I still do that.  It's horrible and you need someone to help you.

DB:	Right because you can't.  Your poems are fairly memorized, almost all of them.

LG:	Lots of them.

DB:	And especially when you're working in the book, like when you're going back through, you're hearing it.

LG:	Your eye makes substitution so unless you read it out of order, i.e. backwards, you're going to be doing that.

DB:	Yeah.  Okay.  That was the first section but there's not much to it because it's mostly digital but then this is more practice.  So I've kind of delineated the writing process into kind of a three-step sort of thing.  So there's the composition, there's the revision, and then there's the sort of organizational archival point, and that's just my kind construction for this interview.  If that doesn't make sense to you, we could talk about it in different ways.

LG:	It's fine.

DB:	I have kind of like the beginning questions which is kind of to give us like an idea about the arch of your career and this question I'm sure you'll love, but how long have you been writing professionally, would you say?

[00:35:00]

LG:	Well, I was trying to write professionally, I have been writing since I was a child and I had a very high opinion of my early works.  So I was sending books out to publishers in my early teens.

DB:	Oh really?

LG:	Well, they were uniformly rejected but I did have that intense dream and I developed it as anybody has to, a very tough skin.  I mean, I have enormous vanity so every time one was rejected, it didn't matter that I was 15 years old.  I thought, "I'm never going to write better than this.  This is the climax of my vision and no one wants it."  That was hard but I continued to send things out and when I started working on what became my first book, I was in my late teens and from the time I was, I think 23, until it was published I think when I was 25 something like that, I had I think 28 rejections, a real lot but I had some poems in magazines but all of that was in place by the time I was probably 12.

DB:	That sort of the ambition and drive.

LG:	Yeah.  And then there were long periods of not writing at all that continued to be harrowing and I had different mechanisms for trying to get through them, the greatest discovery was teaching because I finally learned after the first really lengthy... this is completely off the track of where you want to...

DB:	No, it's absolutely.... my next question is describe the arch of you career so this is pretty much...

LG:	Oh all right.  Well, the first time that that happened, the first one had been published, I pretty much done what was in me to do.  I had also formed, evolved a style in which there were no complete sentences.  They were just little bullet-like fragments and every time I thought to write, I could no longer -I can't make the sentence so it's going to be grammatical - but I could no longer, it struck me, "Write a sentence."  So I realized, there was something about that particular wall that I had hit that had to do with syntax and I thought I have to write poems like no one saw on this blindness that are all one sentence, or as close to that as I can manage.  I couldn't do it.  I couldn't do anything that approached it and I couldn't, at the same time, write fragments anymore.

	The more I couldn't write, the more I repatriated the world.  I thought that the problem was that I was too worldly, too involved in the world, too diverse in my interest so I became more and more hermetic and dedicated.  I would sit at this - I was living in Provincetown for part of this time in New York City - and I would sit in Provincetown at a very beautiful desk that was made for me by my photographer boyfriend with all of these marvelous objects to gaze at and I think it was just horrifying, and, you know, on a good day, I would write an article – the- and on a really good day, there would be a noun- tree - but, you know, we never moved, I couldn't get beyond that and I thought, I had not consecrated myself sufficiently.  There needs to be more forswearing.

[00:40:00]

LG:	I had a bed of nails kind of life, just sitting in the sort of soup of my failure for a year.  During that time, I had one or two teaching job offers.  In those years, it was very much easier because autonomy was different than, you know.  There weren't all of these NFA programs, especially if you were female.  I had a book out and I don't know that I would have gotten a 

10-year track job given my spotty education but I could certainly, I had these offers and I kept saying, "No, no, no, no" because poet shouldn't teach.  I mean, there was that long list of things poet shouldn't do.  They should never have children.  They shouldn't teach.  They shouldn't go out in the world.  They can eat but finally, I was invited to do a colloquium in Vermont and I hated Provincetown but I didn't know how, I didn't want to just begin moving in a sort of ‘pin the tail on the map' kind of way.  I was making my living as a secretary.  I could have done that anywhere in that period but I thought I'll just stay here until the future presents itself.

	So I went to do this colloquium partly because John Berryman was there and he was a hero of mine, and I wanted to be able to pay tribute to him.  I wanted to say, "You are a great artist and I salute you," which I did get to say, but he thought I was just, you know, a chick on an egg.  I didn't know how to say to him, "You don't understand.  I've never said these words."  In any case, I realized about the minute I got to Vermont, I thought I was supposed to live here.  I just instantly loved the place.  It was a four-day thing and there were all these English teachers at Goddard College, hippie institution with a naked dorm and things like that, and they said, "You should come here and teach."  I thought, "Why not?  I'm not a poet.  I have to face this disastrous fact and make a life."  So I said yes and of course they weren't empowered to offer me a job.  They were just drunk and English teachers who liked me.

	By then, I had had a sort of epiphany and I corresponded with two of those people who are my still oldest, dearest friends, Ellen Voigt and prose writer Kathryn Davis.  Three days before the semester started, there was a job cobbled together for me for one semester, and I moved to Vermont and I got a room in a rooming house with the bathroom down the hall.  The minute I started teaching, I started writing again.  I still feel about teaching that is a kind of, it's the most miraculous thing I've ever discovered because I can't always write.

	Long periods go by and I don't write, but I can always teach and I will always meet people who fascinate me and who are doing things, who have minds that go places my mind has never gone, and I won't find that stuff in books by dead people I'm contemporaries, new sounding stuff and it changes me and electrifies me, and to work on material that is still malleable, it was the experience of working on my own stuff but I didn't feel competitive.  I didn't feel.... A lot of that was so strange because I am very competitive by nature but not with my students and I wanted those poems to be as great as they could be...

[00:45:00] PART 4

LG:	...Or in my view and so still, that has served me very well and especially once I discovered undergraduates because I could know them for four years and Williams was nirvana, you know.  I got there and I thought, "I'd never been around such smart people."  I was terrified but I also was thrilled and a lot of those years were years when I couldn't do anything but then some of them were years when I was writing a blue streak.  I'm teaching and it was never I teach one semester and then I write or I teach and I write in between classes.  No, I mean, if I was writing, I would write when I taught.  In fact, after the experience in Provincetown at the sacred desk, I have a horror of the special place, the secluded cabin, the writer's retreat.  I just can't bear them.

	And I want to be without tools.  I often have no pencil and no paper, so I have to borrow them or buy them, but I don't want to presume anything.  If there's going to be a line coming into my head that would be great.  When I'm working on something, then it.... so the shape has always been periods in the desert, you know, without language and then work, which was, after I was 50, most of my books written very fast, like in 6-8 weeks.

DB:	Which book did that start with?

LG:	The Wild Iris.

DB:	The Wild Iris.

LG:	And after that I thought I can do anything.  I can fly planes and I remember my husband saying, "You are going to really hit the wall very soon," and he was right.  I developed neurological symptoms.  I had not slept the whole of that summer practically and one side of my face started twitching.  I had to teach that fall and I remembered sitting in class like this so that nobody would see that my face was...

DB:	Oh wow.

LG:	The neurologist said, "I don't think this is anything.  It will probably go away in a couple of months," which it did but every so often I think something like that could come back again, you know, just some, I mean, it's weird to write that fast and you don't have a sense of agency, very hard to revise because you can't picture... you don't remember writing it.  You just were sitting there and then it was.  The last two books, Village Life and the new one, were slower but they were steady especially Village Life.  The newer one, there were lots of moments when I thought, "This is never going to be a book.  I don't know how to put this material together."

DB:	If you could think back, before you hit this sort of stride, you were producing books very quickly, what was it like, say, writing House on Marshlands?

LG:	Long.

DB:	Okay.

LG:	It took many years.  I revised poems heavily and constantly.  One poem, I remember, took two years to write, for my mother.  The opening lines, ‘it was better when we were together in one body'.  I had those lines in my head for a really long time and at the beginning...

[00: 50:00]

LG:	... At the beginning, I felt very grateful because I thought, "Oh, two really beautiful lines.  This is going to be a poem.  This is exciting.  I have at least these lines to cling to," and then time went by and nothing happened.  No other language attached to that little shard.  So those phrases, that language became a torment.  It was the first thing I would hear in the morning and murmured in my head, and the last thing I would hear at night.  But it was a chastisement, a torment, "You don't know what I'm for."

DB:	Right.

LG:	And I tried to convince myself it was a haiku, you know.  I thought, "Well, maybe it's just a very austere, abbreviated poem," but I didn't think that and nobody I showed it to thought that either.  So that took really a very, very, very, very long time to write and had lots of different approaches, and ended up being a kind of collage of pieces of language from different old poems.

DB:	During that time, you just were working on the one poem? 

LG:	I was for a long time, yeah.

DB:	So there weren't other poems coming in?  Is that traditionally how you work, it's just one poem and then the next poem and then you finish?

LG:	Yeah and then sometimes there will be a massive revision.  One edition to an accumulating manuscript makes it clear how the thing should be ordered and then you see.  You can make a lot of short, little changes in the other stuff because of this new thing.  So some of the books are slower, the earlier books were revised much more, the later books, less.  Though there were revisions in all of them and though most of them preceded at some point rapidly from, I would say, Averno on, there were hiatus.  Like Averno was written into fast periods.

DB:	And the age one in October because I mean that was such a good chapter and then...

LG:	Yeah and I had October and I had Prism, and I thought these two poems can't be in the same book.  I mean, they are just complete opposites.  Then there were two years when I wrote nothing.  I haven't attended to this in recent years but for many decades, I kept this chart of what I wrote when, and each year would be written at the top of, no... the years were like that and the months were like that, and if I wrote a poem then I would write its name and if I wrote nothing, I would write in ‘X'.

	When I got depressed, I would take this out and I would see all these lines with X's and then they would be, at the end, there would be a little gust and the little gust would be completely different from what had preceded the X's.  So I began to be, I mean, trust is a little strong but I just figured, this is how it goes with me.  There's a period usually now after I finish something of being happy because I don't have to write, I feel kind of on vacation, and I have a sense of secret pleasure because no one has seen it and no one has anything to say about it, but I love it and it's finished.  Like last year was such a happy year for that reason because...that's on tape.

[00:55:00]

DB:	I'll send you little clips.

LG:	Yeah.  I'll give it to them.  They made me take my plant, this beautiful antique trunk in the hall with Celadon vase of pussy willow.

DB:	Yeah, I remember that.

LG:	It's still foregrounded in my brain.  Anyway, so all the rest of those poems in Averno were written after this two-year gap and very fast, really fast.  None of it figured it out.  I mean, I didn't have, for 7-80, I didn't have...

DB:	You would have to sort of...

LG:	I didn't have any of the rigging.  I've been reading a lot of Henning Mankell and I was trying to put an image from each of his novels in one of my poems.

DB:	Oh, okay.  Is he a mystery writer?

LG:	Yeah, Swedish.  I hate travel but I was...

DB:	Is this the Nero Wolfe book?

LG:	Nero Wolfe?  No, that's different.   That's Rex Stout.  That was from much longer ago.  No.  Mankell is living.

DB:	Okay.

LG:	Swedish, married to one of Ingmar Bergman's daughters.

DB:	Wow.

LG:	Yeah and I think he is a genius.  I love those books.  I think he's a great prose stylist.  I would recommend them.  Start with One Step Behind, though.  Don't start at the beginning because the first book is not good and you wouldn't read the rest.

DB:	Okay.

LG:	But very dreary, compelling.  His detective plods ahead and he notices small things that don't make sense and turns them over in his mind.  But he is not a fire brand and he is not handsome.  There's a kind of dreary saying this to his days, but the books are fantastic and what their notion of what triumph is.  Triumph is persistence and then it turns into comprehension, you know, a pattern is revealed.  They are real.  I love them.  So I was reading those and I think something of his prose style crept into my poems.  I don't know that another person would think that but...

DB:	In Averno or...?

LG:	In Averno.

DB:	Did it transfer through into A Village Life at all or no?

LG:	No.  That was it.

DB:	That was it.  That was his book?

LG:	Yeah.

DB:	Okay.  So you had your sort of first period of silence after Firstborn and until you started teaching at Goddard, was it like that, sort of repetition every time?  I mean, if you finished a book, you had the pleasure but then you also had the silence or sometimes you jumped...?

LG:	No, sometimes, yeah.  With Marshland, there were a lot of silences.

DB:	During the composition?

LG:	It took about six, seven years.

DB:	Okay.

LG:	I mean, Firstborn was published in 1968 but it was finished in ‘66 and House on Marshland was ‘75.  It didn't, I was put in touch with Dan Halpern and he was starting Echo by Stanley Kunitz.  Stanley said, "This young sport loves your work."  I thought I don't want to have to send this out 28 times and so I thought, "I'd just go with someone Stanley recommends who loves it."  It was published pretty soon after it was done.  So that was a very, very long period but I feel as though Firstborn is just an artifact from another life and that really by writing, life began with House on Marshland.  I think, you know...

[01:00:00] PART 5

LG:	... I can see how each book came out of its predecessor after that.

DB:	What do you mean by that?  Could you point poems in the previous book that were harbingers of the next or sort of turns of language?  I know you speak in your interviews about how you go through and try to eliminate the language of the one book before you move to the next.

LG:	Yeah but even in that sense, so that you, certain stylistic takes you, you try to recognize and prohibit the way I tried to prohibit fragments, but they seem like the work of the same person on some sort of journey.  I try to make them as different as possible.

DB:	I'm interested in what the work of doing that is.  I mean, you've just lived with these poems so often that you recognize immediately what the stylistic ticks are and that they are easy to do or is it something that when you read through the book and it is finished for me, like, "Oh I see that and I see that, and these are the things that I need to really work about eliminating."

LG:	I never see it when I'm working on the book. 

DB:	Yeah, which should be probably suffocating.

LG:	Yeah and so it's only afterward, I think, "Well, I can't do that again" and then sometimes you see things like, "Isn't it odd?  I've never used a contraction ever," and then you think, "Well, I guess I have to figure out how to use a contraction" and that becomes a whole, well, what you realize is that that's co-TV and speech.  That was what I hadn't used and so then in order to use contractions and questions, the Delphic voice evaporates and the human is introduced in its place.  That was a hard moment because a lot of people who admired my work, admired it for exactly the thing that was now no longer present.

DB:	What period was this?

LG:	Triumph of Achilles.

DB:	Okay, so coming in The Triumph of Achilles, that was one of the ticks to.... 

LG:	Yeah.

DB:	Or that was one of the changes that was being made?

LG:	Yeah.

DB:	Right.  So Triumph of Achilles to what's the next one?

LG:	Ararat.

DB:	Ararat and then Meadowlands and then The Wild Iris.

LG:	No, other way, Wild Iris, Meadowlands.  It's okay.  You're pretty current.

DB:	I'm pretty close.  I've been reading the collected and it's so interesting to kind of like move through the time as you're moving through.

LG:	Yeah.

DB:	What did you feel about that, I mean, by publishing the collected poems?

LG:	Oh, it surprised me because I always thought it was a terrible idea.  Well, first of all, it's not the collected and I didn't think of it as that, but it's 50 years of writing.  I was initially appalled and then amazed at its size because I thought it would be about 300 pages long, and then when Miranda said initially 688, I said, "No one will buy this.  We have to squeeze it.  It has to get littler."  I thought it was a valedictory gesture.  I thought it was suicidal to do.  Most of my life, I was repelled by it in principle.  The idea of doing it myself was horrifying.  I had begun to feel, I mean, I never read my old books.  I have no reason to but at some point, I had to do something from a bunch of books where I had to do reading and I was asked to do more of that.  So I was reading through the books and I didn't hate them.  I mean often, once you finish and you're euphoric, and then pretty soon you feel a sense of humiliation and shame.  You just don't want to think about what you've just done.  So then after that you don't go back...

[01:05:00]

LG:	... and then you're trying to prove you can write, writing something else, or, you know, the book gets horrible reviews and you have this feeling of "I'll show you.  You wait.  I'm going to knock your pants off," and of course the people's pants don't come off.  But I was reading these old books and I liked them.  I was proud that I wrote them.  I remember a couple of years ago I sometimes do Tarot readings with Dana Levin.  Dana's sister is a professional clairvoyant and Dana is very good with cards, and I trust her greatly

	 So we were doing one, I guess I had done like cards with Dana but then Dana's sister, Karen, the clairvoyant, was visiting her so we had a three-way conversation on my birthday for a birthday present about the reading.  Karen asked me questions sort of the way a shrink does, you know, leading questions.  She said, "What have you been thinking about?"  I said, "Writing."  Somehow, it came up that I was very frightened by this pleasure that I was taking in my old work because I feared it meant I would do no new work.  Karen said, "I think you have to embrace that.  I think that's..." she didn't use words like path but, you know, "that's what you have to do.  You can't pretend that you're not feeling it.  You just must follow that feeling and see where it leads."

	So where it led was to a readiness to see these books all put together, which had been proposed earlier.  In fact, I was contractually obliged to do it but I would never have been pressed.  And there was always the problem of the fact that Ecco owned most of the books and Dan Halpern resented for a very long time, possibly still continuing this moment, my switching publishers, which I did simply because it's interesting to be elsewhere.  I miss the attention.

DB:	In which book was it did you move?

LG:	Averno.

DB:	Averno.

LG:	It was a very inflamed parting and for a long time, he wouldn't relinquish any of the books he owned so none of that was possible, but it was fine because I didn't want it.  Then somehow, that was all negotiated and I did want it.  I found it invigorating and generally a very pleasant thing, and it made me feel I didn't have to do a big square thing anymore.  Anything that I did was gravy and I really like this new book.  It's not like anything else that I have done.  It's sort of surreal.  It has got prose poems in it.

DB:	That's going to be a shocker.

LG:	I don't think people are going to like it or understand it.  I think of it as very kind of lighthearted or with a kind of, well, there's a lightness in it, a kind of casual shrugging bravado that I like.  It's not beautiful like certain of the lyric books but a lot of people think it's terrifying because a lot of it is about the end of time.  But it's not written as a struggle and it's not written as capitulation.  It's written as, what do you know.

[01:10:00]

LG:	Yeah, sort of like that.  I mean, there are poems in it that are not like what you do, you know, that kind of scratching your head thing but I kind of marry bleakness.

DB:	Yeah, that's always a pleasurable place to be.

LG:	Yeah, anyway, so...

DB:	Did you find in actually writing those poems that there was a different way, like physically you were going after them or anything else?

LG:	Well the last couple of books I've written a lot of it longhand which was a great surprise because everything up until Averno was written on a typewriter, all of the composition.

DB:	Including Firstborn?

LG:	No, Firstborn was by hand and then everything from Marshland until Averno was composed on a typewriter.  It's one of the reasons that my papers are not valuable because there will be pages with little scribbles but usually, I just put in a new piece.  So if somebody who goes through all of these typewritten drafts, unless the person happens to know my work intimately...

DB:	Wouldn't know that.

LG:	They don't, you know, it just looks like a lot of typed poems with no author's hand apparent.  I started keeping a journal when I had whiplash and someone said, "You should start writing about what it feels like because you'll discover that you're not in as much pain as you think you are."  Ha ha.  I mean, I certainly was, but I started this notebook recording my whiplash symptoms and the agony that they entailed.  I always did it in bed reviewing my day and it became the most crucial piece of my day, that and listening to the telephone weather forecast, which became Village Life.  I figured that out but it took a long time.

	So I would listen to the weather forecast and then I would redial and listen to it again.  There was this wonderful voice that would say, "Good evening, Boston," and you would realize that the same thing was going to happen to everybody.  You weren't just selected specially to be rained on, you know.  Everyone was going to have rain and it was the first time I actually understood that everyone was going to have something.  I mean, all those times, I'd stood in the drug isles of the supermarket thinking, "Louise, they can't have made all these products just for you.  Someone else is buying these things," and then I would think, "Yeah, they are buying them but they only use half whereas I need 10."

	Anyway, but the weather did make that knowledge present and meanwhile, I was writing my whiplash symptoms and I would get in a very spacey place, and so I started making notes for poems.  So as not to interfere, confuse things, I did the poems in the back of the book moving toward the middle and my pain journal from the front, and then I'd start a new notebook.  After the whiplash went away, surprise, there were many other things to complain about in daily life.  So this sort of diary of grief, complaint, misery, fear, chronic anxiety, occasional nice things reported, but mainly, the book was sacred to that and it was a real source of sweetness in my life.  Even when I didn't have a bad day or I didn't have any real pain...

[01:15:00] PART 6

LG:	... or I wasn't sick, I felt that I owed it to the book to say the worst.  So there would always be that and then there would be these notes.  So I have a whole bunch of these eerie notebooks and then I realize that it was working kind of well.  Once I started working on the poem, then I would work on it the way I always had, only a lot of it was longhand because I look at, and the lines were getting different shape.  The advantage of that was I could also do it when I was commuting.  So I had a car service in those years and Averno was the first thing I did when I was at Yale.  I remember working on the poems in the car and then I would transcribe that into the notebook in the back.  At a certain point, each one would have to be, there would be enough material so I had to play that on the typewriter and see how it looked in type.

	One fact of working on the typewriter that's either, I don't know whether it's an advantage or not and I imagine for prose it would be.  My prose writer friends all love the computer but when I get to an impasse or an awkward line, I have to start over.  So it's a new sheet of paper and you have to do the whole thing again, and so problems emerge in those retypings, like your fingers will hesitate over something you thought was resolved and you realize it's not resolved.  You realize you have to do something different.

DB:	So you were kind of making those revisions in the actual transcription work.  They are coming to you, almost like a practiced feel of the rhythms or whatever.

LG:	Yeah, your hands wouldn't type it.  You realize something was wrong, either the line was wrong and how it was lineated, which would be simple to resolve, or the whole trajectory of the poem is awry.

DB:	And then you would have to go back and do more. 

LG:	Yeah.

DB:	At that point, would you do more work in the notebook before you went back to the typewriter or once you ....

LG:	It varied, and then I started working on it.  What would happen would be I'd have these typewriter sheets and I would start working on them but in the same timeframe.

DB:	Okay, sort of back and forth.

LG:	Yeah.  They cancelled the weather report, by the way, because of the omnipresence of that.

DB:	Absolutely.

FEMALE:	I have to go feed the meter.

DB:	Okay, great.  Do you have a visitor pass?  We parked with a car.

LG:	Yeah.

FEMALE:	Sure, I can move closer.

DB:	That would be easier and then you could just park right here and then we can give it back to her.

LG:	Make sure you're in a legal place.

FEMALE:	Yeah, as long as it is in the permit parking.

LG:	Yeah.

FEMALE:	Thanks.

LG:	That won't work.

DB:	Were there any other things like the weather report for any other books?  I mean, did that ever happen before?  Were there any sort of other...?

LG:	It was Village Life really that was...

DB:	No other books had like something where, like a ritual to which you were responding in some sense?

LG:	Well, Wild Iris was the garden.  I mean, I had been reading garden catalogues for two years.  I have two years of writing nothing and all I had read was garden catalogues, plus I'd seen when I first moved to Vermont the clairvoyant who told me I would write five books, and I have written five.  Ararat was the fifth.  I thought, "That's it" and I thought, "It's obvious because there's no beauty in Ararat.  It's just the whole lyric gift is dribbling away.

[01:20:00]

LG:	I read garden catalogues and listened to Don Giovanni for two years and I thought I'm brain dead, you know, of course I can't write.

DB:	And that came in a burst, like February or something I think?

LG:	No, it was summer.

DB:	Oh summer, okay.

LG:	I started walking around the garden, which had been the only thing that I did, and things were coming out of the ground and I thought, "I'll try and write something about a flower."

DB:	Now we have an idea of handwriting to the typewriter and what not.  What was it like when you were just typewriting your poems?  I mean, you'd sit down at your desk or wherever.  I mean, the typewriter is one of these things.  You have to be one place wherever you were.

LG:	No, it would always be episodic and it didn't have to be my typewriter.  For example, I remember when I was working on, what was it The Seven Ages, Vita Nova, I remember writing some of those poems on an airplane.  I wrote two on one transcontinental flight and then I got to Irvine and I had to borrow a typewriter.  But that was possible and then I had to work it out on typewriter.  So there were things that were, but at that particular point, I was really on a roll.  I mean, I knew everything was turning into a poem.  So I felt I could be anywhere and I could write with anything.  I could write with food coloring 

DB:	Charcoal.

LG:	Yeah and I could make actually very crude, like PowerPoints, and I would know how to assemble them.

DB:	Oh that's fantastic.  So when you're in that sort of stage, are they just coming to you?  Are they coming from overheard statements or it's all just there and you're just kind of waiting to release it?

LG:	It's nothing overheard.  It's just some weird brain corner that suddenly you have access to and it's like a temporary shelter.  It exists for a very short time and it's not like you think I could go back there.  You just think.

DB:	Do you see any patterns now that you've had these experiences happen again and again that sort of anticipate your getting to where that brain corner opens up or is it mysterious?

LG:	No, it's always mysterious and the last two books have been a little slower in what I felt was a good way because the stamina called for in that other kind of composition is so extreme.  Plus you don't get a very prolonged experience of immersion.  You get a very intense, fast hit but I really liked the feeling that I had.  It was like writing a novel.  In Village Life, I had this sound to go to that was like a place and it was accessible.  I could get there.  It wasn't like this special trick pony.  It meant that the composition was a year, which still seems pretty fast, but it's not as fast as six weeks.  That was Vita Nova.  That was the fastest.

DB:	Six weeks was the fastest.  How long was Wild Iris?

LG:	More like nine weeks but there were three poems that were written the year before.  They just were crap but once I wrote The Wild Iris, once I wrote the bulk of that book, the crappy poems didn't seem so crappy.  One of them, did you know Elizabeth Langston, David and Meredith's daughter?

[01:25:00]

LG:	Did you know David and Meredith at all?

DB:	No.

LG:	You didn't take a classics class?  Well, she's my godchild and she was, at that, point very little.  This was up here, you know the child was writing nothing and I said, "Elizabeth, give me a title or a first line," and I thought if Elizabeth asked me to write a poem, I'll have to do it, and she did and it got used.

DB:	What was it?

LG:	Red Rose on a Lowly Vine.  It didn't get called that finally but it was a little songlike valentine of a poem. But then, I mean, if it looks to you like that's your output for two years, it's bad.

DB:	Yeah.

LG:	But it had a place in that book.  In the name, Wild Iris was the first book I wrote fast but it had these three weakish poems that became absorbed into it.  So I don't know.  I don't know what will happen now.  I imagine I'll descend into some abyss and that is just the question of how much more you get to do.  I'm still feeling surprisingly happy with my last one and I know that until I hate it, nothing is going to happen.

DB:	How long have you been finished with it?

LG:	It will be a year in September, so it's still a baby.

DB:	How do you know, I mean, you have a kind of really final sense of finality for these things and I guess I'm interested in how you... do you have like a physical sensation when that happens or your brain stops moving in that direction and it's off?

LG:	Well, you can sometimes have that but it isn't finished.

DB:	Okay.

LG:	I mean, that has happened to me a number of times.  It always means that there's something that isn't written yet even though you just can't imagine what it is.  Meadowlands was like that.  I thought, "I can't write another of this," but it was clear.  I was putting books together and I can figure out what each body of work seems to need, and there was no way to put that together.  Something was missing and I thought it was probably some more song or its tone, but it wasn't that.  It was Telemachus was missing. 

DB:	Oh okay.

LG:	And I wrote those poems in, I think, 10 days, and then it was a breeze.  I mean, the whole thing came into place.

DB:	I like that book.

LG:	I like that book too.

DB:	It's very funny.

LG:	It's very funny, I know.  I think it's a sprain.  I like that.  I mean, I like tonal variety a lot and I like it in what I read.  But I think the last two books, I drove people crazy with Village Life because I had maybe 400 different orders and they were all not right.

DB:	I could see that being difficult to put together.

LG:	I knew where I wanted to start.  I knew where I wanted to end but...

DB:	In between.

LG:	And I think it was a matter too of something needed to be added.

DB:	How did you learn, I mean, did you learn how to put together books like this?  What was the sort of your education of that sense, each book?

LG:	We learn from the material and I think I learned from students too.  I think that I'm a very good editor.  I always felt if I had stuff on a page, I would have some good instincts about, I mean, if it was anything to be gotten out of that material, I would find it.  So a sort of sense of...

[01:30:00] PART 7

LG:	... being able to put to use the most pathetic, limited samples of language but if you just give me some words, it doesn't matter how bad they are, I can do something.  And I felt the same about manuscripts.  I thought, "If there's a way to put it together, I'll find it," my own books and other people's books too.  I mean, in a way, I'm sure I drive some people crazy because I just look at their manuscripts and I say, "No, just leave it all to me.  You're doing this terribly."

	   I was that kind of a mother, you know.  I would say, "Don't feed yourself, really.  You just don't know how to do it.  You sit I'll feed you."  People don't like that and it's also possible that one could be wrong or that there could be something I miss, but I think it was something that you learn when you write very slowly so you don't have a huge outpouring.  You have a small amount that you have to make, go as far as you can."  So you learn how to move the parts of the poem around.  You learn how to be an editor out of a sense of lack and from that grows a capacity to organize disparate things into something that has a sense of dramatic shape.

DB:	That sort of a sense of dramatic shape, is that your intention for most of your collections?

LG:	I want the books to seem like that but it's not as though when I'm working on them, I know what it is.  I pretty much don't.

DB:	When do you get that sense?

LG:	When I'm starting to put it together.

DB:	When you're starting to see them all together.

LG:	And then you start seeing these weird overlaps and resonances and echoes that you hadn't planned.  I mean, proofing my new book, I see the strangest parallels and language recurrences that, I mean, you could say, yes, you have a limited vocabulary and so of course there's going to be a recurrence of these words that you use because you still remember them, but it's also that, it's like dreams, you know.  Somehow, the mind is making an organization that is beyond what the comprehending or apprehending faculties take in initially.

DB:	So when you're working just on an individual poem and you're revising it, what's like the mode there and you're going back, are you just deleting, are you substituting, or whatever the poem needs, you're kind of in service to it?

LG:	Yeah, the aim, I mean, if I can tell myself that a poem can't be made with just deleting things, that's great.  That's two for the price of one.  You get the deleted lines.  If they are any good to use somewhere else and you get a poem, but oftentimes you can't just delete often.  Sometimes you can take out everything that's weak and transitions that are obvious, but what you then wrecked is the feeling of duration the poem has become to risk and needs to have a feeling of more languorous unfolding.  So then that's a problem because you don't know whether you're supposed to...

[01:35:00]

LG:	... add in the places where you had material before or were they the wrong places, was that part of the problem?  But each poem is its own little task.  You know for a long time, it's a problem you haven't solved and then it becomes something that you have solved.

DB:	Yeah, is it the same feeling of finality that you have with the collection that you have with the individual poem that there's nothing more to be done sort of thing?

LG:	Yeah but also that it gives you pleasure, that you like the shape that it makes and you like it better than you thought you ever could.  So all these poems, you just thought were so cumbersome and there was no way that they could be organized.  You just didn't see it.  Suddenly, you actually like them again.

DB:	Has your mode of revision, has that changed at all over the course or has it been fairly consistent?

LG:	I'm sure it's quite different but I wouldn't even have a say.  I mean, the poems are so different that it must be that the approach is different.

DB:	Right.

LG:	I mean, now I'm much more like approximation.  I like a sense in the poem of not the sort of honed perfect [ball mold 1:36:50], you know, the epigrammatic.  I want more that kind of speech.  A sense of casting about for a phrase, I like that feeling.  Human sounding, ruminative rather than exalted, but you know, I think of Averno as, the book has always seemed to me, I've said this a million times, this is probably on there already, some of these books seem vertical and some of them seem horizontal.  Usually, they alternate, so there will be a kind of awe to despair book followed by panoramic book, but the last two books seemed to me kind of spreading. They are very different from each other.  How many people are you going to do this with?

DB:	10.

LG:	Jesus, you'll be out of your mind.

DB:	I know, it's okay.  You're number seven, eight.

LG:	Oh you've done a lot.

DB:	yeah, I've done quite a few.

LG:	Does everyone sound different?

DB:	Yes, it's very interesting what people want to talk about.  I've done people who know me and who don't know me and so there's some weariness and sometimes there's not.  Sometimes the people who know me are weary of the questions more.  Honestly, the questions haven't really been asked but you've answered them without my asking them, so that's good.  It's a good sign, I think.

LG:	I hope so.  Well, we could do it again if you don't have anything to use.

DB:	No, I think there's plenty.  So when you're revising, are you reading them out loud to yourself?  Is it part of your craft as some of the other writers has been...

LG:	I keep trying to make this point in poetry readings.  I hear with my eyes.  I mean, the experience of reading a poem, for me with my eyes contains an oral experience and when I hear it, I feel angry and I feel that there's an obstacle between me and the ‘it' of the poem.  The obstacle is the reader who is determining and deploying emphasis...

[01:40:00]

LG:	... and also the form which is turning a kind of web-like experience into a narrative.   Everything goes by once and the argument made is "Yes, but then you can't hear it," but I don't hear it when it's read to me and I don't moderate to myself.  I hear it in my head though and I hum it in my head.  I mean, I can hear...

DB:	You can hear almost like musical notes or tones?

LG:	I can hear rhythmic structures.  I remember with Meadowlands, I had this sense of the book.  It was the only time I had this.  I felt I had a whole book in my head.  I just didn't have a single word but what I had was rhythmic alternations.  I had shapes that were clustered and then some more open shapes.  It was almost as though it was a musical line and I would hear the rising and the falling.  I would hear choral parts.  I even tried to annotate it in some way so that I could follow it but it was like a hum.

	It was like, I heard somebody say, a thinker of some kind not a poet, something about the way a child learns speech, lying in its cradle and hearing the shapes made by the speech that surrounds it.  It doesn't understand words yet but it understands, and for me, poems had been like that.  I mean, I remember reading when I was really, really young, reading not baby poems but great poems, Shakespeare's songs, and I have no idea what was being talked of, none, but I felt I was getting something out of those poems.  I could hear fear no more the heat of the sun.  I could hear the grandeur of that, the rhythm.

	Somebody could turn it into an act of scanning the line but that makes it so kind of plodding, but I did hear things that way but with my eyes.  I mean, my eyes make, I turn what I see not into argument or a reasoned thing.  A lot of that stuff I miss.  What is the poem saying?  I often don't, I have no idea but I know how it sounds.

DB:	Because it sounds sort of intelligent communication too.

LG:	Yeah.

DB:	That's really fascinating.

LG:	Well, I'm sure there must be a lot of people who write who have this, who feel that sound comes to them visually.

DB:	It's almost anesthesia, right?  It's close to that sort of description but it's not, not quite really but it's an interesting correlation.

LG:	Yeah.

DB:	I know you work with fellow poets on your poems, correct?  I mean, you're sending stuff to certain readers, etc., do you work on individual poems at individual times or is it usually in a collection?

LG:	Everything I write goes out.  I want someone to look at it preferably right away, right now.

DB:	Who are those people?  Have they been the same people for a long time or they change?

LG:	They change.  I mean, it's certain periods, certain people.  Sometimes you'll feel somebody is, you feel these poems if they are ever going to be understood by anyone will be understood by X and you're usually right.  When X says, "This won't do," you trust it because the person is basically on the side of the work whereas if you show it to somebody who...

[01:45:00] PART 8

LG:	... from the outset say, "This is just a disaster,"  The book has to be, you know, it's too late to unwrite it.  It's going to get written and you could then suppress it if you want it but, so it shifted.  I mean, there are certain people who have been constant for a very long time.  Kathy Davis, she has been stratospherically helpful and I like working on her novels.  I learned a lot from working on prose.

DB:	What have you learned?

LG:	You learn moving around much bigger pieces.  I mean, Kathy's books are not so much a question of that but there have been books where I felt there are too many characters and these two could be inflated.  Other times, I felt things were in the wrong order or that too much time was spent on a particular thing, but with my former husband who was a quite terrific prose writer, it was often a question of reading, moving around blocks of prose the way you would do in a poem.  You'd move a line in the poem but in prose, you would move a paragraph or two paragraphs.  So I learned, it's like weight training.  I could move bigger masses and it was very useful.  I mean, I don't think I would have written Ararat without that and I think if I hadn't written Ararat, I would have stalled out as a certain kind of lyric poet.

DB:	Right.  Well, I have some questions about why you chose not to use a computer.

LG:	I'm epileptic and I didn't like, I learned but I didn't like looking at the screen.  The early computers, it was said it was not good for epileptics.

DB:	Okay.

LG:	I didn't like it.  I liked paper, I liked pages.  I love typewriters.

DB:	What do you love about typewriters?  It's a big question.

LG:	Doesn't everyone love typewriters?

DB:	I don't know.

LG:	I don't know.

DB:	Is it a sound thing?  Is it a feel thing?

LG:	No.  I actually, since the period of burning my hand, I don't type anywhere near as well because I don't have perfect feeling in that finger, but it was a sense of how sort of slovenly handwriting became form.  I don't get that on the screen.  I don't see lines on the screen quite the same way and I don't feel as though I'm making the letter, well often I'm not.  I'm making the wrong letter.  I don't know why I like it.

DB:	But it has been such a consistent part of every book I guess.

LG:	Yeah.

DB:	We could skip all these computer questions.  You correspond with many people.

LG:	Yeah, well I used to be a much better letter writer.

DB:	Has that changed quite a bit, I mean, with receiving and you're sending out with the kind of computerized or has that, is it just sort of...?

LG:	Yeah, it has changed a little but long before I had my little red friend, I had stopped writing letters the way I once did.  I mean, there was a period in my life when, even like 10, 12 years ago, I just wrote lots of letters to lots of people...

[01:50:00]

LG:	... And I loved getting letters back and I loved writing letters, and then that stopped.  I don't know why it stopped.  It wasn't because of that.  What I have noticed with this is I have now a correspondence with my first husband whom I had, we would exchange letters every two years or something, very formal letters.  Then there was a period in which he needed somebody to confide in who was far away and so we had a little period of much more intense exchange, very short.  I saw him and met his current wife.  I saw him for the first time in 38 years, last summer, and we liked each other and I thought his wife was just great.  I mean, I felt no sense of... this is off the record.

DB:	Okay.

LG:	No sense of, you know, I should have stayed with him at all, but I liked him and we started corresponding this way, briefer but it seems the right form for the two people we are.  It's helpful to kind of substitute for a phone call when you don't feel like making a phone call, and it gives people a chance that they would have with a letter but not a phone call to respond when they are ready to and not have a moment forced upon them in which they have to react.  I have very happy thoughts about this.  It just has nothing to do with writing and then I think it was a big moment when I switched from longhand to the typewriter.  Maybe it would be equally transforming to switch to a computer but not an iPad.  I would need a real keyboard but I can't use a mouse still.  I can't.  When I see that little thing, it makes me very squibbish, upset.

DB:	It has to be a touch screen.

[end of audio 1:53:00]



    </transcript><rights>Copyright Devin Becker, all rights reserved.

    </rights><fmt/><usage/><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation/><xmlfilename>gluck.xml</xmlfilename><collection_link> http://www.devinbecker.org/ctrl-shift/</collection_link><series_link/></record>

    

</ROOT>

