<ROOT>
    
    <record><version/><date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2014-06-16</date><date_nonpreferred_format/><cms_record_id/><title>Kasey Mohammad interviewed by Devin Becker</title><partial_transcript/><synopsis/><keywords/><subjects/><gps>42.185762, -122.695772</gps><gps_text>Ashland, OR</gps_text><hyperlink/><hyperlink_text/><accession/><duration>00:57:44</duration><collection_id/><collection_name/><series_id/><series_name/><repository/><repository_url/><interviewee>Kasey Mohammad</interviewee><birthyear>1962</birthyear><residence>Ashland, Oregon</residence><interviewer>Devin Becker</interviewer><file_name>mohammad.mp3</file_name><next>beasley</next><previous>pinsky</previous><sync/><media_id/><media_url>http://www.devinbecker.org/mp3/mohammad.mp3</media_url><mediafile>
        <host>Other</host>
        <host_account_id/>
        <host_player_id/>
        <host_clip_id/>
        <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
    </mediafile><language>english</language><index/><type>application/mp3</type><description/><rel/><transcript>
        DB:	I missed like the first 5 minutes of what we're trying to interview.

KM:	Oh, no!

DB:	I think I got it on one device, though&#8212;but not recorded.

	This doesn't end up like the most reliable thing. So...

	OK, should I close that or...?

KM 	You might just so people don't bug us.

DB:	OK

	Here we go...

	Alright, so we begin. Thank you very much for agreeing to do this, KC.

KM:	My pleasure for coming.

DB:	Would you please state, for the camera, your name, your date of birth, and the location we're at right now?

KM:	Kasey Silem Mohammad. October 10, 1962. We're at Southern Oregon University in Central Hall.

DB:	So, the first section is kind of short-answer. It's meant to get a sense of you digital practices now. So, we'll just kind of go through this and we'll talk more about the composition.

	So, what genres do you work in?

KM:	Poetry

DB:	OK, and that's your primary genre?

KM:	Yeah

DB:	What kinds of devices do you own, or have access to for writing?

KM:	This laptop, a MacBook. That's... I mean, that's about it, other than whatever scratchpad I might put my note my idea in.

DB:	So you use only that one? Do you write on the phone? Do you write on any other things?

KM:	Usually, not. I mean, the laptop is the main instrument.

DB:	The laptop is the main instrument?

KM:	Yeah

DB:	And you have an Apple.

KM:	Uh-hmm

DB:	Do you then....You said you use some note papers sometimes?

KM:	I mean, if I'm somewhere and all I have is a piece of scratch paper because I'm in a meeting and I get an idea. But that's... I don't really do that often.

DB:	OK, so it's pretty primarily on that computer?

KM:	That&#8212;that is mostly it.

DB:	OK, do you have any... I mean, for your writing... This is where we get to the... Do you ever take like pre-writing or notes for it, or ...?

KM:	Because of the kind of writing I do, that usually doesn't come in to play.

DB:	Yeah

KM:	Which I think will become clear when we talk about the actual composition. 

DB:	OK

	In what format do you save your digital files?

KM:	Word

DB:	Word doc

KM:	Uh-hmm

DB:	Do you save individual works as you go along, or do you simply save over what you've written? Do you have like... Do you save  like drafts?

KM:	Oh, no. I don't... I probably should, but I almost never save drafts. Just open up a doc and write over it until I think it's finished.

DB:	OK, and what are your naming conventions for your files?

KM:	Usually the name of the poem, followed by the file name.

DB:	Yeah... But... And so, because you don't use drafts, you're just like...It's just the one?

KM:	Yeah, I don't rename it once I've drafted, or anything. It just stays the same.

DB:	Do you ever.... Do you print out your writing to revise it?

KM:	No, not typically.

DB:	OK

KM:	What exactly... I mean, I might do that on occasional like with an essay because I need to be able to.. It's easier on the eyes. But the poems are usually shorter, and again because of the specific nature of the composition, in some case, you will see it's like I can't revise it really well at all if it's not on a computer.

DB:	Yeah

	And so, if you don't use... Do you ever save any paper copies of interim drafts?

KM:	Usually not. I think the only exception to that is maybe I have some paper copies somewhere of something I wrote in college (and hope no one will ever sees&#8212;maybe it's the way they're written.  I don't ever bother to try and describe them digitally).

DB:	So, do you back up your work?

KM:	Yeah, when I remember. Yeah. 

DB:	And how often do you do that?

KM:	Oh, gosh. Conscious of streaming&#8212; I don't know. I probably need to do it right now&#8212;excuse me. I really... It's very erratic.

DB:	OK

	So, do you use... You don't use like a Cloud-based...Do you have like Dropbox or anything? I mean, is that...?

KM:	You know, I've got a server here on campus. It's a backup server  everything it into. It's very simple. All I need to do is drag stuff right now (and I could do it to stop bothering about it).

	I've also got an external hard drive at home.

DB:	You have an external... And that's if you're going to archive it, if you're going to back it up, that's where you put the work. 

	OK

	And say... Do you have like a separate thing for ... Once a poem is finished, do you move it to a different folder, or are there any...?

KM:	Yeah, I've gotten kind of lax on it. I need to go in and update it, but typically what it'll be is: I have a 

(05:00)	folder (a main poetry folder) and within that, if there is a specific categories for certain projects, I'll divide them in to that (like a book project, or whatever). And if something is published, typically, I'll put a copy of it in the Published folder, and then there would be like an Ongoing, or In-process, folder.

DB:	Yeah

	Do you keep print copies of final drafts? Do you print them out?

KM:	Not usually. 

DB:	And how about the media you've been published in&#8212;do you keep the journals or... in a sort of space?

KM:	I do, yeah. I have a shelf full of journals and books. 

DB:	OK

	So, do you have any standard practices for archiving digitally or physically? Would you say...?

KM:	Maybe explain what you mean a little more.

DB:	I guess... I mean, do you have... Like when you put it on... Do you have like a certain kind of way you go where you put it on an external hard drive, or you put all your papers, or your books, in a certain shelf and that's kind of like your archive?

KM:	Yeah. Right, yes. Like I said, I do have a shelf in my living room. It's like most of the journals and books, anthologies, I've been published in. And as far as I said for the digital files, yeah, there's usually a Published folder&#8212;which is way behind being updated.

DB:	So, have you ever received or sought out information about digital archiving, or any sort of practices in that way?

KM:	Not really, no. No.

DB:	OK

	Would you be interested in receiving information?

KM:	Possibly, yeah.

DB:	OK, that was kind of the basics.

	And so, this gets more to the kind of like your trajectory as a writer. So, it starts off kind of getting a larger arc of it. So, how long have you been writing "professionally"?

KM:	I'd say since roughly '98 or '99

DB:	'98 or '99

	And could you kind of give us a sense of like the arc of your career over that time period?

KM 	Sure. 

	That's when I was just finishing grad school (and procrastinating on finishing my dissertation). So, I kind of went back to my long-time interest in contemporary poetry. And I think I had tried to send a few things out to get them published over the years, a few times, without any success or sense of direction about it.

	And then during all this time (wasting period), I became aware of electronic journals for that publishing authors that I liked, but before that I hadn't known even how to submit work, you know, to the same journals that would publish poems I liked because, you know, I had tried&#8212;missing, for example, 5, 10 years before to submit to magazines that I knew published language poetry and things like that. And typically, I really did get no response, or maybe a slip saying, "Sorry, this journal is no longer in circulation," because the only way I heard about them&#8212;the first place&#8212;was from the library copy... I had no contact with any of the people involved.

	So, the internet changed that. I've published in a few online journals and made contacts with poets that way. And then it was pretty rapid&#8212;from an initial Chap book that was published by Kenning Editions (ran by Patrick Durgin in 2001) called Hovercraft, then my first book (in 2003) was Dearhead Nation from Tougher Disguises Press by James Mets. Then another book (next year), Mike McGhee's combo books A Thousand Devils; a couple books at the end of the decade from Ed Rodsmith's Jury, and lots of journals and anthologies in the middle there. And a few other Chap book that I've neglected to mention.

KM:	And then... And now, the project that you're working on the Sonograms?

DB:	That's my chief project, yeah.

KM:	OK, but you have other ones going?

DB:	Well, that's the one that I consciously think of as a project that I'm in the middle of. Occasionally, I'll write something just on a whim, but yeah, that's the main project.

	So, we'll sort of talk about in the.... couple of different steps   in the writing process and then we're going to go through kind of how it was in the early stages of your writing and how it's changed. And so, my kind of way of thinking about it is there's the compositional stage (which is where you're kind of creating it), and then you have the revisions stage, and then you kind of have the organizational/archival stage (which is when you're putting it in to books and getting it published). 

	So, those are the 3 stages to talk about. And then how those have changed over the course of... Sort of like 3 by 3.

KM:	Sure	

DB:	So, when you first started writing (and this is even before you started writing professionally, maybe before when you were trying to find those language journals, or language poetry journals). I mean, what was your composition"? Or, how were you writing, like what were you doing?

KM:	That's really hard to reconstruct something that long ago. 

	I don't think I have much of a method. I think I was really just kind of feeling around in the dark.

(10:00)	So, I took a couple of... You know, I took a couple of creative writing classes in junior college. I took one as an undergrad, but didn't really work for me. That didn't do anything for me. Yeah, and I just occasionally feel inspired to write something. I mean, I was very shapeless.

DB:	Yeah	

	So, how did you come to find the writing that you like? I mean, to find the language poetry, to find the journals that you were sending out?

KM:	I don't remember what led me to it, but I remember just surfing the web. I think one of the journals, one of the very first journals that caught my attention was Combo by Mike McGhee. They published Clark Coolidge and other language poets (and younger poets I hadn't heard of), and then at least some of it was online (I think if I remember correctly it was like limited to digital sampling). And I just emailed them saying, "Hey, I just want to go about submitting any work," or anything like that. They liked the work, and I was published in them a couple of times.

	It's the same thing with Kenning (which is also a journal&#8212;Patrick Durgin's journal). 

	I think my first publication actually was in Fourteen Hills from San Francisco State. I went to a group reading for the contributors to that issue and met a lot of Bay Area poets. So, I established a connection with...

	I forget what the original question was now...

DB:	Oh, it's fine. That's actually kind of what I'm interested in.

	And then... And so, your writing styles in the beginning, the ways of composition, you are kind of formless and then you started accommodating...

KM:	Oh, yeah, yeah

DB:	How did they start to progress then? I mean, what was sort of the next step in...?

KM:	Sure, that's actually pretty easy to answer because it's kind of, at least so far, it's been kind of a really distinct, 3-stage process.

DB:	Oh, great!

KM:	Actually according to the terms of the question.

	So, that earliest work&#8212;and this would be everything up through the period I am talking about&#8212;was just basically (I don't know how quite to describe it) organic, or free-hand, and you know, just making stuff up and writing it down. Words would come in to my head, and I would put them on the page.

	So, typically, I would just type and it would be like trying to compose a musical piece, or something&#8212;like, what should go after this; how can I complete this rhythm (or set of images), or something like that.

	And then that began to change with (again 2000/2001) when I met Gary Sullivan and other members of the Flarf Group&#8212;and that itself has kind of like 2 stages. At first, I became acquainted with Gary's writing on an email list that we were both on, and just for a joke he wrote some New Year's poem (or something like that) that he called a Flarf poem. Flarf was the invented name for the method. It was basically just writing the stupidest, most shapeless thing you could think of&#8212;so it was full of non-sense and obscenities, and phatic noises with no real shape, or form, other than just basically roughly being broken in to lines.

	He and I (and a few other people) started doing this for fun and we created our own email list just so we can do it (and I'm sure the full origin, stories out there about...) ....

DB:	Yeah, and just for my clarification. It started on a different email list and then it moved to its own?

KM:	That's right, and I guess really it started the list (if I'm correct&#8212;I think this is what Gary related to me)&#8212;that he sent a poem in to one of those online vanity price things [inaudible 13:55] .com (and the short version) trying to get rejected. So, he wrote just the stupidest thing he could think of&#8212;and "it was accepted for consideration for the anthology" which he then pay for if you're actually dumb enough to go through with that.

	So, that was the origin of that. Now, they just started writing them more on the email list even after he realized he couldn't get rejected&#8212;because it was fun. So, a group of us that were on this list... And so eventually (I think it was Drew Gardner who introduced a method in the middle of this shapeless writing) of using Google search results. Just going in to Google page, doing usually a combination search for like two or three terms that you don't expect to see on the same page together, and then using that initial search result page as a base from which to collage excerpts&#8212;not following the links, just...

DB:	Just the language that shows up in the Google 

(15:00)	like the caches, or the...

KM:	That's right, yeah!

	So, my typical process... This is the 2nd stage&#8212;the big 2nd stage where, for 10 years, I basically just wrote Google collages. The typical process for that was I would copy however many pages of the search result page (next page, next page of about 10 or 100 results show up on the page), and the page turn in to word, and start chiseling it down (rearranging it, shuffling the contents&#8212;occasionally cheating a little bit, putting a connector words or something or maybe altering a word in just a slightly different grammatical form or something).

	But that gets back to what we are saying about not doing print revisions because really everything is done with (kind of like refrigerator magnets) just shuffling around. And I guess printing out a page, I can look at that thing and, "Well, if I brought some of this down here, see it all"&#8212;but I never did that, so...

DB:	No, right, right. I mean, it makes it kind of it's computer generated.

KM:	Yeah, and part of the fun of it was using the computer as a kind of canvas.

DB:	Yeah

KM:	There's kind of something pleasing about pulling the components around&#8212;almost physically moving them around that digital space.

DB:	And when you're copying the page, do you just say CTRL + Alt, grab it, drop it in? Do you get images and what-not with that? Or do you just like drag the thing up and just get the text and paste it?

KM:	Yeah, I typically just select the whole page, copy, paste. I mean, there weren't any images because it was just the result page.

DB:	Just the result page, OK

KM:	Right	

	What you would get is a lot of the red or blue text, or purple text, the URLs and headers, and things like that, but typically I would just... You know, first stage of going through the manuscript would be to remove all of that kind of junk text. It wasn't all junk but...

DB:	Right

KM:	But, yeah they were just numbers and code, and so all I had left were recognizable words, maybe numbers.

DB:	And in getting rid of that (of that junk text) were you reading it at the same time or were you starting to kind of get a sense of what you have gotten? Or was it just kind of a rope&#8212;"Let's get rid of this and I'll look at it"?

KM:	 I think... Based on my memory, it'd be a rope thing of just, "First, let's get rid of everything I know is not actual, (in most cases) not useable text." I mean, there might be some little strings of code where I think, "Oh, that's kind of cool just by itself. I'll leave that in," but it was mostly an automatic process of just, "Let me reduce it to just letters and black text (as opposed to colored, link text).

	And then from that stage of... I don't know how interesting this could possibly be to anybody but...

DB:	I'm interested!

KM:	What would be left after that would be a lot of things like ellipses, or dashes because there'd be partial phrases, and then ellipses, and then a beginning of another phrase--that'd be how the search results would be arranged on the page. So then I might just have to say, "OK, I might get rid of all or most of the ellipses or dashes" and I would also, I know, go through (just for the sake of composition) change case&#8212;select everything and then change case to lowercase just to get rid of all the blocks of long list of caps that are kind of unwieldy.

	And then later in that process of composition, I might change some letters back to caps, but typically for whatever reason, the default form after the poem would be no caps unless they're required convention (by which I mean like proper names and things like that). Now, I wouldn't capitalize the beginning of a line or anything like that.

	So, I'll just start... Basically, once I'm ready to actually start composing the poem I would have however many pages of full of lowercase language in black and white. 

DB:	Yeah

	And so for the dashes and ellipses and what-not, you'd just do a Find All and delete them all?

KM:	Yeah, that would be the quick way. I learned that pretty quickly. I would just, "Find this, replace with nothing" until I just have words to fill those parts, maybe some numerals.

DB:	Yeah!

	And so, you would get to the.... And so... I mean, that's almost kind of your pre-writing stage in some ways, and then you're to the point where you're composing the poem or whatever word you want to use. I mean, what words do you use, I guess?

KM:	Yeah, and then after that.. I mean, once... Just because of the nature of the way it was copied on the page with, usually what I end up with would be something like a tercets, or something that looked on the page already kind of like tercets which is why a lot of the poems (not all of them) end up being in tercets, and I would just keep that&#8212;and sometimes 2 lines, sometimes 3 lines, sometimes longer, and 

(20:00)	sometimes more (longer) stanzas.

	But sometimes, just that accidental form would give me kind of a starting point like, "OK, I've got groups of 3 lines, but I want to move this line from this one up here to this other one. And then balance out the other one with the other line (or phrase)." Like I said, it would be like refrigerator magnets with all those sometimes full phrases instead of just individual words. 

	And in the middle of that process, I usually get rid of most of the language&#8212;some of the language I couldn't figure out what interesting thing I could do with, or would be interesting. 

	So, the finished poems might be anywhere from a third of a page to several pages long, but I'd be starting sometimes with like 10 pages. 

DB:	And you just go and delete, delete, delete?

KM:	Uh-hmm, and rearrange, shuffle.

DB:	And so, what were the phrases or the words, or groupings, that would catch your eye or catch your ear? I mean, which was it catching, I guess, too?

KM:	I'd say earlier in the process, it had more to do with the original search for terms I used. So, for example, my first book Deerhead Nation involved a bunch of searched usually included among other terms the term deerhead. So, for that, I was obviously motivated to keep deerhead a lot of the time so I can keep that theme going. Or sometimes I would think of a phrase I think was funny or bizarre and I'd want that to be a title, and I want to keep a few instances of those words in the poem. 

	I'd say it's like a... Several years along the process, I got to the point where I didn't really care if the original term showed up at all. I just wanted to create kind of a lyric construct, but that was limited for its sources&#8212;that bank of terms. 

DB:	What do you think got you to that sort of preference?

KM:	No idea

DB:	No idea

KM:	I think just getting bored with the regularity of the earlier process. So, I think, it worked pretty well for me, yeah, with some of the original first projects because they were kind of thematically motivated. You know, the deerhead thing was supposed to be kind of a metaphor for Imperialism or something, I don't know...

DB:	Yeah

KM:	But as it went on, I just really became more concerned with just wanting  a verbal shape or sculpture that I found interesting.

DB:	And do you find that those later poems are more like readable, or... I mean...?

KM:	Probably not. I mean, that's a good... I'm laughing, but I mean... You know, one person's definition of readable is very different from another's because, in all honesty, some people would look at whether it's early in the stage or later in the stage and think, "This isn't poetry. This is just spam (or something)&#8212;garbage from the internet." 

	I don't even think that the divide is along the experimental or traditional, necessarily, because frankly a lot of the biggest critics of Flarf are experimental poets. 

DB:	Right

KM:	So, I think it really just have to do with whether a person has that kind of mind that likes arrangement, in that sense, rather than... Let me rephrase that. I think it depends whether someone's drawn to verbal arrangement over and above verbal theme. 

	I mean, that's what drew me originally to poets like Clark Coolidge and other language poets, or... You know, it didn't matter what it said in the traditional sense. I was interested like, "Wow! I can put those words in that place!"

	So, I don't really know what's readable to the "average person" because I don't think there's an average person.

DB:	Yeah

	I guess, in terms of your own reading or in terms of your own compositions, I mean, when you're making those things, did you find those later poems to be more pleasurable to make? I mean, was there like... I don't know. You said there was more of a lyric bend to them.

KM:	Yeah, but I don't know if other people would see those lyrics necessarily. But, yeah, I think so. I think... Inevitably, it became almost (at least from my perspective) more traditional. I mean, yeah, I don't think other people are going to think, "Yeah, you call this traditional?" but I felt like I was kind of going back to the kinds of things that pleased me about older forms of poetry. So, even if the poems themselves have like ridiculous vocabulary and images, junk food, or porn site terminology (or whatever else comes off the internet), I would be looking for rhythm&#8212;I would be looking. 

	I'm very influenced by somebody like Clark Coolidge on that level&#8212;kind of like the jazz influence mode of composition.

DB:	So, I guess... I mean, how are you constructing your lines, I mean, if you're looking for that sort of rhythm?

KM:	I mean... I guess, the lines are really just determined by the 

(25:00)	shape of the phrases. I mean, for me, the rhythm comes outwards, from words. It's not like a pentameter rhythm or something that's determined by a set length. It's a not-nap [inaudible 25:13] project, not-nose prose [inaudible 25:15]

DB:	But then, were you grabbing... When you grab a phrase or a few phrases, we're those automatically lines or would you break those into different lines. 

KM:	It really depends, but I usually do a lot of breaking. I mean, there's a sense on which the whole process is kind of unnecessary, I mean, because ultimately what I was doing was just manipulating the results so much that... I mean, I would think all the time that   I really don't need to go to the internet except at the level of just, I think, vocabulary.

DB:	Yeah, yeah

KM:	And maybe beyond that, just a little syntactical clusters--"Oh, wow! Look at these 4 words in a row. I would never have come up with these 4 words in a row on my own just trying to think of something." So, what I was looking for is just really pallet full of colors&#8212;colors I couldn't think of by myself because, you know, human being would think of putting those things in a poem because they're not that, they're something else at that stage.

DB:	So, in terms of like your revision strategies for these poems, I mean, in the early stages you had  a more (I'm sort of recapping) intent towards representing the search in some very fundamental way, and then later it started to become...you wanted to kind of represent an accumulation and arrangement more lyrically, or more in a way that kind of traditional in your traditions of poetry.

KM:	But in the one constant was the importance of the idea that was generated by the search, and I think that was a factor for the re-... I think, I don't see the need to mask the method. I think, one of the pleasures, for me, of reading other work like that by other people is knowing, "Oh, they did this by using a particular procedure." And I'm still most interested in how the finished work affects me, but the knowledge that it was created in a certain way is something I can't separate, and I don't want to separate. 

	So, you know, I would frame the work all the way through. It's like, if I were to mention it which I had occasion to do in the beginning of the book if ever-- "This was creating using Google search methods." So, I think it helps people going in to it with that knowledge, but like you're saying, I didn't necessarily want the search to retain some imprint of it&#8212;all the original conditions of the search&#8212;maybe in the first book, to some extent, yeah.

	For example, in Deerhead Nation, I not only kept a lot more longer clusters&#8212;the original syntactic clusters&#8212;but I would keep a bunch of ellipses and create visual groupings with them. All these kind of graphic reminders of what the process was. I just felt less inclined to do that as I went on because it didn't seem necessary for the different kinds of poems I was getting in to.

DB:	Right, right

	What about the prose poems in this traditions? How did those come about?

KM:	Oh, yeah! I mean, same thing but there the original search terms did remain much more important because, I mean, you have a phrase like "and then she said" or something very fixed and obviously in order to keep the shape throughout the poem, I'm going to have to keep coming back to that tag. Then there the goal is usually to make it seem seamless like this is the one subject saying something over and over again. So, yeah, that would be an exception whenever I do... although I think I also did some prose once where I didn't stick that much to whatever original, grammatical framing. I don't remember off hand how...which ones. 

DB:	Yeah

	So... 

	[I'm trying to think how to phrase this one] And then...

	[So, we're at that...] Well, I mean... I guess this is one of the questions I ask a lot. It's: were these revisions driven by sound? I mean, were you reading them out loud to get a better kind of rhythm or did you have like meanings or themes that you wanted to, let's say... I mean, especially it seems...?

KM:	Yeah, that's a good question.

	I think sound was probably usually, at least, tied for the primary way there. 

DB:	Yeah, and what would determine a line break then, in terms of sound?

KM:	 That's a difficult question even for like traditional methods of writing, right?

DB:	It's an impossible question.

KM:	You know what drives me crazy on workshop when I'm teaching? It's like on the one hand wanting people to think about line breaks and what motivates them in what they do, and the other hand getting so tired of getting bogged down in completely arbitrary theories of like the line break because, in some ways, 

(30:00)	it's like the very important thing is just totally random. I mean, not in every poem obviously and, of course, especially if you're working on a fixed form, it's taken care of but free-verse or procedural (or other kinds of things where the line breaks are kind of post-facto consideration). I mean, really? It's just going on my nerve, you know. Just what strikes me at the moment is seeming like the good way to keep the rhythm going, or to create a [inaudible 30:29] rhythm, or do a little both depending on where I am in the poem.

DB:	Sure

	Did you... And so, for these... OK, what would be the phrase that you would use? I mean, you said it's collage. .You say it's Google collage. I mean, I've seen Google sculpt. I've seen [inaudible 30:46] poetry--

KM:	Yeah, Google sculpt is the term I kind of put out there for it.

DB:	OK

	And then... So, that's the one you sort of prefer saying. It's like Google sculpting&#8212;I mean, sculpting being collage works?

KM:	Collage works, too, yeah.

DB:	Collage works, OK.

	And did you save... Like do you know what the terms are for each poem, and is there somewhere where that's recorded?

KM:	No. Sometimes I think about that, "Why didn't I keep a record of how exactly this came about?" I'm too kind of absent-minded and lazy for that.

DB:	That's OK

	Probably have to recreate it someday by using simulator or--

KM:	Oh, you can't because the internet has completely changed, right? 

DB:	Yeah

KM:	It's gone forever.

DB:	I know, I know. It's so fascinating.

	And then... So, I guess those are... That's... So, we've moved from the first stage to the second stage to then the 2 stages of that. The latter stage of that having run up to about 10 years you said?

KM:	Something like that, yeah. So, like I'm writing just free-form or however you want to describe it from like '98 to 2000. So, that's very short phase. The second book, A Thousand Devils, was kind of stuff left over from that stage. So, even though that came out in 2004, most of it have been written quite earlier.

DB:	And the Hovercraft is also that certain stage?

KM:	Yeah, that's that initial stage.

DB:	OK, and then the second stage starts with Deerhead Nation?

KM:	Uh-hmm, through Breathalyzer and The Front.

DB:	And The Front, OK.

	And then... And now, the project... And so, this third section then is the Sonograms?

KM:	Yeah

DB:	So, how did that project come about?

KM:	And I should just... I mean, just discuss what I say, I'm calling these stages just as a convenient way of separating different times.

DB:	Well, it helps my kind of--

KM:	Yeah, yeah. I just wanted... I don't think of it necessarily like, "Oh, this is the, you know, initiatory stage and I developed in to this." This is just when I happened to start doing and stopped doing.

DB:	Yeah, no. Not compression. It's more of just--

KM:	Yeah	

	So, yeah, Sonograms... I'd say... I forgot what year. Maybe... It's embarrassingly a long time now because I've been working very slowly on it. I've been a really lazy poet.

DB:	The best poets are.

KM:	And so, I mean, it would've been finished a long time ago if I kept it in schedule, but I'm a little over halfway thru. I think I started (I don't know) 2008, or something like that, and it started... It was like National Poetry month, and I was looking for an idea for like&#8212;just some quick and easy gimmick to allow me to write a poem a day. And I thought, "I could do something with Shakespeare sonnets." It's like go to the internet and find a sonnet, copy it, and post it/ paste it in to a Word doc--"OK, what can I do in the next 5 or 10 minutes using this as my source?" Say, "here I wrote a poem for this silly tradition."

	And I just started kind of shuffling it and playing with it with my cursor, thinking. And I had been recently impressed by a book (by Gregory Bets) which I'm not embarrassingly forgetting the title of&#8212;anyway, it's a book in which he takes a paragraph from a speech and rearranges it multiple times throughout the book just by a letter. So, anagrams of the same paragraph.

	Yeah, Christian Book gave me a copy of this, as well as... I think Gregory Butts was with him at the time and say, "Hey, you'll like this book," and I did. I thought, "Oh, I want to play around with it," and I suddenly remembered, "Oh, anagrams. Well, OK. This will probably take too long. I'll just start shuffling it around like figuring out ways to break it up." And then, I came up with the idea of taking each of the lines and feeding them in to an anagram generator because I felt it would fit (at the time, it'd be one line). 

	So, I did that, and every time I feed it in, the anagram generator would give me a choice of a bunch of word lists that you could make by rearranging that particular line. I just picked the one I liked the best until I had this poem that was 14 lines with silly words. So I thought, "Well, OK. There, that's a poem. Eh, that's not that interesting..." I mean, it was kind of cool.

	And in retrospect, that was kind of thing I wished I had done: was to save all these initial first stage word lists that I used to create the poems&#8212;

(35:00)	but I haven't. 

DB:	Librarians are sort of cringing right now.

KM:	Because they were kind of neat poems&#8212;like cheap, fake poems on their own. They're just line by line anagrams of the original sonnet but without much syntax or anything, they're just words in a row.

DB:	Right

KM:	So, I sat there and thought, "Oh, I'm already 10/15 minutes in to it. I'd be more interesting if I move the letters throughout the poem like Gregory Butts did." So, I did that and like 4 or 5 hours later.... I had been working on these poems for like a big chunk of the day. And then I got really hooked on it and started doing a bunch of them. I don't think I kept to the whatever it's called, the National Poetry Month schedule, but I did a few of these and I soon it stuck. Now, I'm up to 90 something evidently. It's embarrassing.

	Like I said, it's 2008. I should have a lot more.

DB:	And there are?

KM:	154 total

DB:	154, OK

KM:	So, yeah, each poem is just an anagram. And then, I would say, there's a sheet that I'll use all the letters to create a new poem in iambic pentameter with the original rhyme scheme (A, B, A, B etcetera), 3 quatrains and a couplet, but then I'll have letters left over. Almost it's never a problem that I don't have enough letters, usually, it's just I can't use them all in the poem. So, I have to use those extra letters and make up a title, and that usually is pretty stupid. The whole poem is stupid but the title isn't in pentameter or anything. It's just whatever I can do with the leftover letters.

DB:	Duh

KM:	Right, right

DB:	Yeah, so, when did you... So, you had... You started off with the kind of stuff from the anagram generator (and I'm assuming that's not in iambic pentameter).

KM:	Right, just words 

DB:	So, when did... Was that the initial move that first day you went and you're like, "Oh, I need to make this," to match up with Theo's [inaudible 37:11] sonnet format?

KM:	Yeah, yeah. That was pretty much it. I think the very first one was the one on this little trading card.

DB:	Oh, I have that&#8212;trading card.

KM:	Yeah, I have it somewhere with me. Hiding, but... Frankly, in fact, it's definitely the worst out of all of them because it's got sort of a consistence in text and grammar but it's just complete nonsense. 

	[I don't know... I can't find it, but...] But it was, in fact, technically iambic pentameter and they technically rhymed&#8212;you know, half rhymed. Then I got much more stringent about from them on like, "Oh, I got to actually make them construable as meanings even if they are bizarre meanings."

DB:	OK

	And so from that first one on, you were kind of... From 2 to wherever you are (up to 97, you were like, "OK, now I'm going to have more structure to them"?

KM:	Yeah. I mean, they always have the structure. I may be overstating it. I think, the first ones probably in some ways are construable than the others. I just... I think, it was just finding my stride like for the next field like, "Oh, I don't have to reach for these like half rhymes or..." I can make that the most determined, kind of fluid part of it, and just then make the absurdities stand out even more pleasing relief.

DB:	I mean, you said they got better as you did, and I'm sort of interested in this from your early Flarf stuff to The Front, too. I mean, it does seem that there's... I don't know. From my... In my taste, I think, it's better. And so, I'm wondering like what.... How do you think of it that way? Is it just from the practice? Is it from--  

KM:	I think really it's that simple. I think after the first 1 or 2, I just got more practice working with the pentameter, creating a smoother flow. Really, that's all.

DB:	Right, and so now that you're almost number 100, I mean, what do you... I mean like do you have a different way of going about it? Do you have a different--

KM:	The basic process stayed exactly the same. I think I changed the generator at one point in the process because I found a better one.

DB:	What was the first generator?

KM:	I don't remember what the first one was. It was kind of like a standard&#8212;like the one where most people would come to first, I believe. And the way I chose it, in the first place, was it was just one that would accommodate an entire line because not all of them would. Usually, they're just better with just like names or things like that, but I found one that would take an entire line in iambic pentameter. And then most recently, the one I use now is, I think, the best out of all I've used. It's called One Across.

(40:00)	OneAcross.com

DB:	OK

KM:	And it's nice because it's got a little control. I'm sure all the others have probably developed since I've been doing this, too, and they can do a lot of the same things. But, I'll put in the basic line in the top box and then I have a little, if I want to, an optional box where I can make sure it contains a certain word. So, if I find a certain word, I want to make sure it's in it, but if don't like the first few... Because there are like sometimes hundreds of options to scroll thru, so, it's like, "Make sure it contains lawnmower, you know (or whatever)."

DB:	So, you can limit it by that.

KM:	Yeah

DB:	So, you search and then limit the search in some ways.

KM:	Uh-hmm

DB:	Ah, that's interesting.

	And so, do you ever... Does it ever produce a perfectly iambic pentameter line that you can use?

KM:	I haven't done that yet. I'm sure it's theoretically possible.

DB:	So, is the million monkeys in King Lear, right?

KM:	I mean, you know about the Pentametron which is this wonderful Twitter-based website.

DB:	No, I do not know about the Pentametron.

KM:	It is exactly kind of what you just said. Somebody build a program that just continuously scans Twitter (everybody's Twitter account apparently) and finds all lines of iambic pentameter&#8212;really most of them, I'm sure, are accidental&#8212;and finds other lines of iambic pentameter rhyme with them and create this ongoing poem.

	So, I mean, I can go to it right now.

DB:	Yeah

KM:	And the one thing about it is it always starts with the oldest part. I wish it were bottom to top so you could always see the most recent.

DB:	Yeah

KM:	Oh, here we are. You just go to the Twitter page with that.

	"Bread cards and sweaty bodies everywhere. The largest arms erect in to the air. I'm way excited for the album though, you just a hoe&#8212;a stupid, stupid hoe. Tim Duncan is a fucking dinosaur. I'm not a people person anymore. I wanna wear a maxi dress today. I really wanna sleep the day away," and so on.

	There's also the original Twitter was and just random people. So, it's like the greatest poem of the 21st century. 

DB:	Yeah

	Do you know who's behind it?

KM:	Oh, I don't know. Whoever this is, I don't know them personally. I don't remember what their name is.

DB:	Yeah

	That's fascinating.

	I know that the New York Times had that one where they pull the haikus from, and like make little haikus, too. Similar project, not as good.

	So, getting back to kind of... I mean, do other people play any roles in all these things. Well, I mean.... I guess, I'm interested in 1. How it was writing to the list serve in that early stages. I mean, like in terms of revision and kind of like forces that sort of morphed into your poetry, what was that like.

KM:	That was great. I mean, that... Really, most members of the list would agree, that was the most stimulating about being on the list&#8212;just feeding off everyone else's excitement and creativity because it was very much a big hug fest, right? There was almost nothing critical going on in there ever. We just try to write stuff to bust each other up. And it would be very responsive&#8212;if somebody wrote a poem with farting unicorns, somebody else would write one and expand that (like farting glittery unicorns, you know), and the sillier the better. The more obnoxious, the better. 

DB:	So, that was the sort of frivolous stuff&#8212;on the farting unicorns. I mean, that sort of silliness was very highly valued on the list serve.

KM:	Yeah. I mean, that was kind of the original spirit of Flarf which is to... And I think it's also part of the reason for a lot of the resistance to Flarf from experimental directions&#8212;there was a sense of like it wasn't taking the struggle seriously enough, or something, which, you know... I think what comes out of this, for me, misguided sense&#8212;that absolute stone-face that this is necessary at all times. 

	And, there are times where there are legitimate objections and I'd rather not go in to details. But there are, you know, some poems that upset people.

DB:	Right

KM:	And I think it was very upsetting to the people who wrote them that they did upset people because even though it might seem like "Well, why are you trying to offend people? Why were you trying to get people upset?" I was like, "Well, no&#8212;not these people." 

DB:	Yeah, right, right

KM:	And I think initially we were very resentful about it. It felt like, "Oh, we're on your side and you're misunderstanding us. These are not whatever racist or sexist or otherwise vile intentions that you're looking at 

(45:00)	here." But, I mean, I feel like as time has gone on, I try very hard to be more sympathetic to that response because out of that context that it emerged from, it's easier to see how a poem that mentions certain things in certain tones isn't almost impossible to separate from a poem that mentions those things in that tone with a different intentions. 

	And I think even past Flarf, things like that are going on right now with some of the younger conceptual writers and...Once this work I really admire, when I see other poets I really admire, I'm deeply hurt by the work they're creating. It's very difficult. I don't have a way to kind of like justify any of it, or put it in to order in my mind.

DB:	Yeah, no. It's [inaudible 45:57]

	Would that... I mean, so, what do you think... How do you think... I mean, a lot of your career, a lot of your writing has kind of happened from the internet and on the internet (with the blogging and the commenting), and that seems to have (in some ways) died down in a way?

KM:	Yeah, blogging seems to be a thing in the past, for me anyway.

DB:	Yeah, and I mean, like what... How did that shape your sort of practice, your writing? I mean, you say that you've evolved in some ways about your opinions on some of the content that would be included. Has there been other effect? Or could you elaborate more on that?

KM:	I'd say what I've evolved, at first, in is not necessarily... I haven't changed my mind about some of the (I don't know what you want to call it) starting theory. I've just become... I've tried to become more empathetic and not immediately judge anyone who doesn't get it-- 

DB:	Right

KM:	--Or even, see, even using a phrase&#8212;like that doesn't get it already shows a little residual judgment. There may be more than one way to get it and that some ways don't match our intentions, and that we need to consider that we are accountable for that.

DB:	Right

	Well, in so much of the sort of the... I don't know... the latter part of Flarf has been the sort of death of Flarf, and some kind of the log post and what-not. I mean like was that partly the reaction&#8212;just like "let it go"? I mean, where does it go from there, I guess, is the question.

KM:	I'm not sure how much. I think death of Flarf, most of the time, was  a phrase we used ourselves just to kind of like "trying to kill the beast before it killed us," or something. But I think it just ran its course. I think, like any movement, the movement itself has its main values in the way it motivated the members of the movement&#8212;and most of the writers just write however they're going to write. Yeah, and it's influenced by that, but it's not the same. 

	So, the original question, I guess, was about the blogging?

DB:	Yeah, and kind of how that influenced your own writing.

KM:	I don't know. I think for me, again, the main value of the blogging thing was to bring me in to contact with other poets and having discussions. I think there were a lot of people (in the early aughts especially) blogging every day, and were having fun conversations. For whatever reason, they moved on to other platforms, and other projects. And it also ran its course.

	But in terms of... I don't know. I mean, I think the main effect was just social.

DB:	OK	

	And then... I mean, like... So, I guess one question is: could you have written the Sonograms in the way that you're doing without Flarf? I mean, what sort of influence from there?

KM:	Well, there are certain surface similarities, right? I mean, like the refrigerator magnet process&#8212;I mean, pasting something in to one Word and using that as my template. So, yeah, I think Flarf... I mean, in some ways (at least originally), I considered it an extension of Flarf practice. I mean... I guess there's no way to say that it is or isn't. There's no definite meaning to that. It is if I say it is, I guess.  

DB:	Right, right

KM:	But, yeah.... I mean, I think it definitely... It's probably something I wouldn't have done in quite the same way I did it if I hadn't been doing Flarf.

DB:	What.... What... I mean (and this goes back to some of the questions we were just talking about), what sort of skills did you learn in doing the Flarf that kind of go in  to the Sonograms? What did you come in feeling strong about, and what did you learn without?

KM:	I think it's what I mentioned earlier&#8212;that approach to arrangement: finding clusters, finding strings in already existing groups (verbal groups). Kind of being able to sift and sculpt something that was already in front of me.

DB:	Yeah

So... I mean... I think, we've kind of covered some of the general push through composition and revision, but I'm also interested in how you would put together the books especially if... 

	Well, one question before we move in to that. 

(50:00)	Do you still write in that sort of traditional Flarf way? I mean, are you still grabbing Google responses and--?

KM:	I haven't done it in a long time. I think, I did a few kind of like post-Flarf Flarf poems for a couple of years after I started doing the Sonograms but, eventually, it just... I don't know. I think even the way it's configured on the internet now is such that it doesn't work quite the same way. I don't know exactly how, but... 1 or 2 times in the last year until I even thought about trying to go back and doing it, it isn't the same.

DB:	So, a lot more information like underneath and on the side. I mean, it's just kind of [inaudible 50:28]

KM:	I think, yeah. Part of it is Google has gotten too smart.

DB:	Yeah

KM:	Things are grouped according to usefulness rather than just random occurrence of words--

DB:	And who you are, too. So, yeah...

KM:	It knows me too well, and it's... I don't trust it.

DB:	Google and it'll appear, and never disappear. Terrifying.

	So, I mean... But in those terms, like what were you using? Like how were you composing the books then, I guess is the question&#8212;like Deerhead Nation and Breathalyzer and The Front? I mean, were you... Do you have sec-... You don't really have sections in those books, kind of a [inaudible 51:12], right?

KM:	Really, the only one that's thematically, in any sense, organized is the first one. I mean, with the whole deerhead theme which, like I said, is just a sort of a floating metaphor.

DB:	Right

KM:	For the next... I mean, Brethalyzer and The Front are pretty much interchangeable in terms of how the poems are chosen or grouped. They're just individual poems. And I actually have a full other manuscript that I have been... that may or may not get published from that period. It's just been so long now. Even though I actually like some of the poems there, I thought, "Does anybody really want this now as the time passed?" It's called Monsters, and tentatively it might come out from Edge Books, but I haven't followed up on my obligations on getting the manuscript in. So, I don't know where I stand with that&#8212;I may have screwed it up.

DB:	Did you... I mean, when you were publishing these books (and maybe with Monsters), do you have relationships with the editors&#8212;that they're like revising the shape of the book?

KM:	Well, definitely I have relationship with the editors. I mean, like Rod Smith for Edge&#8212;like fantastic editor, fantastic poet. But he's pretty hands-on in terms of the actual creative content. I mean, maybe in terms of... Maybe... I'd say his input and his helpers' input comes in with the level of things like layout.

DB:	OK

KM:	Yeah

DB:	And then... So, I mean, I know you have also some of like e-Chap books and what-not. Where do those... I mean, what do you feel about those and like how do you end up with them?

KM:	I haven't even looked at them in so long, I can hardly give you a clear answer. I remember some of it was very early Flarf, and again, I haven't looked at it in a long time, I suspect I'll probably just cringe looking at a lot of it because I think what was initially exciting about the process is what quickly becomes predictable and crude about it&#8212;like, "Oh, look! This text comes off the internet. It smells like the internet. Look at it, you can see internet all over it." It becomes kind of obvious after a while.

DB:	Yeah

KM:	But, I don't know... [What's the most recent one like that...?] Yeah, I mean that's a long ago that I...

DB:	And in terms of like the digital documents that contain those manuscripts and those books, I mean, are they in a certain spot in your computer somewhere? Are they... Do you have them...

KM:	I think I just have the original Word documents of them

DB:	Just the original Word docs--

KM:	And whatever else out there, or maybe a pdf in a couple of cases.

DB:	Do you feel in any way (and this is getting back to a more technical stuff) sort of like dear towards them? I mean, do you have like... Or you're just like, "These are there, but really the books&#8212;the book"? That's sort of a leading question, but I... I guess I'm wondering like if you... Are you really taking care... Like is there enough value on them that you make sure where they are and they're valued etcetera, on a digital format, too?

KM:	Well, at least there's that much value that I know I have copies of them. But beyond that... I mean... And again, it's not... I'm not trying to be evasive. It's not that I actually am embarrassed, or have strong feeling one way or the other, it's just that I really don't remember that well what's in them.

DB:	OK, yeah

KM:	Because I was just too much stuff at that time.	

DB:	Right

KM:	I mean, I'm sure if I took a few minutes to look, "Oh, yeah. This one. I like this one," or "I don't like that one so much," but I'm trying to even form a mental image now and... but, yeah...

DB:	So... [I do have a few Flarf questions I wanted to make sure I ask but I think I got through most of them].

	Well, I mean, sort of like... I mean, how does this then influence... 

(55:00)	I mean, one of the questions I ask the other people who teach, and you teach, too&#8212;how does this influence the way you teach? I mean like what sort of... What did Flarf teach you that then you tried to teach them, or anything in that sense?

KM:	I mean... I guess, the single most important thing is just that it has to be fun in some level. Not to... I think it's very... I mean, I wouldn't necessarily frame it as Flarf in the classroom in this way, but I think one of the first things I tried to do in the beginning in the classroom is break down the sense of over-seriousness that sometimes holds people back. So, I'll give them exercises which people are doing a lot before Flarf (you know, write the worse poem you can&#8212;things like that). Or I might, for a specific exercise, to adjust the procedure that is relevant to Flarf but I want to say, "OK, now we're going to write a Flarf poem."

	I try to...There are, inevitably, times when it comes up, or somebody in the class heard of Flarf and say, "What's Flarf?" and the story would get told. But I actually try to hold back on that because too often it results, I think, in exercises that might be fun for the student and even produce humorous material, but doesn't necessarily contribute to the kinds of foundational verbal skills that I want people to concentrate. Or if it does, it doesn't for everyone. For some people, it can be a way to avoid. 

DB:	Right

KM:	So, I guess that's true for everything but--

DB:	And what are those sort of foundational verbal skills that you're after?

KM:	I mean, just really basic conservative things like rhythm, like avoiding clichs&#8212;and just writing something where you're not just recycling received notions of what a poem ought to be.

DB:	Right, yeah. It's all kind of getting towards writing something interesting, making something interesting to a reader, right? I mean, in some way.

KM:	And looking in to source that you might not immediately consider, you know? Encouraging them to read a lot of poetry. Just the really basic things.

DB:	Right, right

	Just  a few more questions. I guess... Eh, no. I think we're good.

KM:	Well, good

DB:	Thanks, Kasey. 

KM:	Yeah

DB:	That was really great.

KM:	It was a pleasure.

DB:	Yeah

KM:	Sometimes I'm croaky, I mean...

DB:	No, it'll be cool, you know, whenever it shows up.

	[Ah... The off button]

KM:	[Are we Friends on Facebook?]

DB:	[I don't have a Facebook.]

KM:	[Oh, OK]





End of Transcript



    </transcript><rights>Copyright Devin Becker, all rights reserved.
    </rights><fmt/><usage/><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation/><xmlfilename>mohammad.xml</xmlfilename><collection_link> http://www.devinbecker.org/ctrl-shift/</collection_link><series_link/></record>
    
    
</ROOT>
