<ROOT>
    
    
    
    <record><version/><date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2014-05-21</date><date_nonpreferred_format/><cms_record_id/><title>Robert Pinsky interviewed by Devin Becker</title><partial_transcript/><synopsis/><keywords/><subjects/><gps>42.371701, -71.107116</gps><gps_text>Cambridge, MA</gps_text><hyperlink/><hyperlink_text/><accession/><duration/><collection_id/><collection_name/><series_id/><series_name/><repository/><repository_url/><interviewee>Robert Pinsky</interviewee><birthyear>1940</birthyear><residence>Cambridge, Massachusetts</residence><interviewer>Devin Becker</interviewer><file_name>pinsky.mp3</file_name><next>mohammad</next><previous>strickland</previous><sync/><media_id/><media_url>http://www.devinbecker.org/mp3/pinsky.mp3</media_url><mediafile>
        <host>Other</host>
        <host_account_id/>
        <host_player_id/>
        <host_clip_id/>
        <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
    </mediafile><language>english</language><index/><type>application/mp3</type><description/><rel/><transcript>
        [00:00:00] PART 1

        RP:	You want me to play to the camera at all or do you want me to play for you?

        DB:	Me, it's fine.  This isn't like going to go on PBS or anything.  It's more archival and then I might make some clips if I ever get a website together, which hopefully will happen.  You are saying that you use the word "compose" rather than "write" because you are using a sort of oral and voice-based mechanism which is your body.

        RP:	For the rest of, it I do all of the above.  I write longhand on paper, I compose on a computer, more process of revising.  I print out.  Like most people, I print out very frequently, scroll over the print out, stare at with the scrolling on the print out is, create another fair draft either in my mind or on the computer.  I number my drafts DR1, sometimes DR0.  I know it's not going to last long.  I've gone up to DR87.  I think in some things I've gone up to DR104 in the file menu.

        DB:	You are using Word in this, Microsoft Word.  When you are using these file names?

        RP:	I tend to use, I always get mixed up.  I think they call it RealOffice for Mac and NeoOffice for Windows, maybe it's the opposite.

        DB:	Oh okay, but it is it?

        RP:	It's basically a word processor like Word.

        DB:	Okay.

        RP:	There is also a neat one that I use for difficult things.  I don't know why I don't use it on everything, I can't remember, called something called Nisus Writer.  I could look at it.

        DB:	Yeah. I have heard of one called Scrivener.

        RP:	No, this is, I think, the state of the art.  I think this is the one and yes, Nisus Writer Pro.  It's terrific at all kinds of elaborate formatting and indexes.  Nisus Pro.

        DB:	Nisus Pro?

        RP:	Yeah.

        DB:	When did you start using that?

        RP:	A couple of years ago but I'll juggle them.  I'll go through phases of a certain purposes, duplex printing on it, non-duplex printing printer.  I know how to do it on Word, so I'll open up Word.  So in a way, I use all of the above but I am not loyal to any particular word processor.

        DB:	Software essentially?

        RP:	Yeah.

        DB:	I guess what drove the getting the Nisus?  Did somebody tell you about it and you just thought...?

        RP:	I probably did some web research but there were things that I didn't like about the NeoOffice page numbering and headers and footers.  It seems clumsy to me and none of these programs are super expensive anymore, it used to be a big investment.  The best one I have ever used was, it's like Betamax versus VHS.  It was excellent but didn't have no followers, Word Perfect.  Word Perfect was terrific, it was perfect and that doesn't always win the marketplace.

        DB:	Not it does not. Word Perfect was in the '90s, I think?

        RP:	I'm an early computer user, so I probably started using it in the mid-80s.  I wrote a computer entertainment in the early '80s.

        DB:	I know, Mindwheel, correct?

        RP:	Mindwheel, yeah.  I just read a new very informative article about Mindwheel.  Although I'm kind of paper tiger in technical things, I don't really know a lot about computers.  I've had to do with them and I've used them for a long time.

        DB:	Since the early 80s?

        RP:	I think it was 1980 when they asked me to start Mindwheel and you can tell how prehistoric, how early that was, but the brand of the computer that they gave me to write it on, they gave me a computer that was an Atari.

        DB:	Do you miss the Atari?

        RP:	No. I still remember that monochrome, yellow, black and yellow monitor that weighed more than anybody's big flat screen TV.  It was immense.  For a long time, anything I wrote to be read on the screen, I wrote on the computer and things I wrote meant to be read off paper, I wrote on paper.  The pen or with the nicest machine I have ever owned, an IBM Selectric.

        DB:	When did you own that?

        RP:	I had a Selectric in the '70s and the '80s.  I often regret that I don't still own one.

        [00:05:00]

        RP:	It was like a BMW.  It was such an excellent machine that golf ball and then the lift off tape, so you could lift, you could erase perfectly.  Because the ink, it was so precise that they had a lift off ribbon and you went to that and back spaced, it lifted the ink off the page and it was a solid machine.  It just did what it was supposed to do so well, obvious advantage, the obvious reasons why electronic, why the computer took over, but this IBM Selectric was a beautiful machine.

        DB:	It's good.  I have not thought of it as a beautiful machine before, but I think that's good to know.

        RP:	Have you ever used it?

        DB:	I've never really used it, so I can't say it.

        RP:	It's amazing.

        DB:	Yeah. Now I kind of want to go and find one.  My typewriter experiences have not been very good.

        RP:	A crappy typewriter is not any fun.

        DB:	And the ones that I end up looking at or using are out of tune essentially.  So, you are a Window user primarily but with...?

        RP:	No. I used to be a Windows; I'm primarily an IOS user now.

        DB:	You're primarily an IOS Mac user.  That is then just a screen that's coming from the MacBook Pro.

        RP:	Yes it is.  One refine, maybe this is the kind of thing you are interested in.  I used to go through the whole [inaudible 0:06:35.4] of syncing between my desktop and my laptop.  I went through various generations of the best way to do that and now I'm not quite at the totally cloud web system, but I realized that with a nice external monitor, external keyboard, external mouse, I can use the MacBook Pro as what we used to call the ICU, then when I'm tired of using that way, I just have to remember to eject the backup and then unplug all that stuff and then I could go to an airplane with it.  I'm not syncing it with anything.  It's itself.  

        DB:	When you save your files, do you have like a Dropbox account or anything like that?

        RP:	I do have a Dropbox.

        DB:	So, you do have some sort of backup in the cloud?

        RP:	I have a Dropbox account and I have a 2 TB amazingly small little white brick...

        DB:	External hard drive.

        RP:	That backs up automatically.

        DB:	How long have you been doing the backups procedures?

        RP:	For years and I'd like to vilify the company, it's a sort of a French name that with the backup failed.

        DB:	Really?

        RP:	My computer broke and the, I can vilify these people, they are called...

        DB:	It's not LaCie. Is it?  No?

        RP:	It may have been LaCie.  Anyway, that can happen too.

        DB:	What happened there?

        RP:	Most stories about, "Oh I lost my book on Yeats, I lost all this," it's about 79% bullshit, most of us have given the manuscript to somebody or have an earlier address somewhere else.  It's never pure loss.  Most things in life it's a matter of degree.

        DB:	Yes. It's true.  So, what was the loss there?

        RP:	I can't remember.

        DB:	You can't remember. It wasn't...

        RP:	I lost a bunch of data and I didn't lose anything that I couldn't recreate or find a different version of somewhere else.

        DB:	Let me look at these ones.  You sort of went through – your first answered many of these questions right here.  It seems like you've been fairly adept at using a computer for most of the time.  Have you sought out any instructions or has it just been something you've taught yourself?

        RP:	It's mostly something I taught myself.  Adept is a relative term compared to all the other writers and poets I know.  I guess I'm adept compared to any 15-year-old.  I try hard and I did.  You know, that first encounter, I've always liked gadgets.  I never was good in school but I always liked learning a certain kind of thing and I guess I'm the type that tends not to like to read the instructions.  I would rather figure it out.  If there are two great personality types in the world, I tend to be the type that says, "If I can't figure it out, I don't want to do it."  I don't want to have to read the instructions.

        [00:10:00]

        I did hang out with programmers when I wrote Mindwheel.  My introduction to the computer technology I did hear a certain amount of jargon and sometimes when technology is from a primitive state, you learn more about them than when they are more perfected.  At one time, to drive a car, you had to know something about cars, people in the days of the term Hi-Fi, they had to know something about the process of recorded music and as they improved the car and they improve... some people who get in and improve recorded music, there is less and less anybody needs to know.

        DB:	I'm reminded of a story about the early MSN messenger wars.  Did you read this with AOL and the MSN people were like going back and forth, trying to kind of copy each other's thing and then the people at AOL started programming in like the basic, basic level.  Like that's called, I think, operative processing or something, and it's like huge, huge amounts, ones and zeros essentially.

        RP:	I think before assembly language.

        DB:	Yeah, exactly.  So, you are way up there.  Can you talk a little bit more about how that came about, how the Mindwheel came about?  Were you at like a location that the programmers were near and they contact you specifically?

        RP:	I was sitting in my office at the University of California, Berkeley.  I was very glad to be at Berkeley after the, for me kind of tedious Wellesley College where I taught.  Wellesley was like going to jail but was a little New England Women's college.  So I was very happy to be at Berkeley and that euphoria lasted for weeks and then Berkeley also came to seem very much like, how can I put this, an English department.  The phone rang and it was somebody named Ihor Wolosenko, last person I have known named Ihor.

        Ihor Wolosenko from Synapse Software and he said, "I'm looking for a writer to work on a new kind of computer product.  Are you familiar with Text Adventures?"  I said, "No."  He said, "Are you familiar with computers?"  I said, "No."  He said, "Have you ever heard of a game called Zork?"  I said, "No."  He said, "It's a text that appears on the screen and you can go North or South or East or West, you can pick up objects.  It's a form of a narrative. We have a very superior program.  We can become more sophisticated than that.  We are interested in serious literal writers who might write text for a game like that.  Might you be interested?"  I said, "Yes."

        It was the first yes I had in the conversation.  Synapse was in El Cerrito, which is quite close to Berkeley.  I went out there and it was not an English department, there were these weird guys with their shirts half tucked in.  I later learned they lived on Big Macs and Van Houten bars.  They slept in the day time and worked at night.  They didn't pay for their phone stone service, they had different ways they could pirate phone service and had little machines that made long distance tones.  The words that were most forbidden I've seen to them were not ratio epithets or sexual terms or scatological terms, the forbidden words were words like nerd.  I liked them and I wrote out several scenarios for Ihor.

        DB:	Those are upstairs?

        RP:	Yeah, it is.  Maybe I should help you find it.  There are a couple of rooms up there.

        [00:00:00] Part 2

        DB:	So, we are talking about Mindwheel.  You went over to meet the programmers and you liked them quite well.

        RP:	I wrote up three or four different plots and the most far out one, modeled vaguely on Dante, the comedian, was you have to get, you are on a mission to travel through these minds, full minds.  It turns out that minds leave permanent elaborate footprints and records of themselves in what we call the... I can't even remember what I call it in the game itself.  I was called the game.  They always called it an Electronic Novel.  At the beginning Dr. Virtual puts the electrodes in your head and then you travel through the minds of a kind of Shakespeare-Dante figure, a kind of political [inaudible 00:06:04] figure, vaguely John Lennon like, a woman who is kind of an Einstein.  She's just there and a great dictator, kind of a stubborn Hitler who is leading mind...

        DB:	You could chose your own adventure kind of thing or?

        RP:	No.  It's more interactive, they called it.  You need to solve problems.  Some of them involved poetry.

        DB:	Did you come up with those poetry with the poetry problems?

        RP:	Yes or I would adopt ones from the 16th century poetry.  There was one riddle, you have to  free a winged woman from a cage and the cage is the riddle.  It comes from Sir Walter Raleigh's poem, On the Cards and Dice, and it says, "An herald strange, the like was never born, Whose very beard is flesh and mouth is horn."  You had to solve that riddle and the Raleigh poem which is there, it's about the Cards and Dice, and it says, "The triumph will be heard and dead bones will jump up, will be rattled and men will groan and four kings will be gathered and four queens."  So, it sounds like a mystic prophesy but it's the Cards and Dice.  Then it says, "They do this until Herald calls, a Herald strange.  The like was never born, Whose very beard is flesh and mouth is horn." I can see your flunking this.

        DB:	I'm totally flunking this.

        RP:	They play all night.

        DB:	I'm so flunking this.

        RP:	Something wakes them up in the morning.

        DB:	The rooster?

        RP:	Yeah.  Whose very beard is flesh, his beard is horned, the rooster is not born, it is hatched.  Even so when I was a kid, you weren't born you were hatched.

        DB:	So, you incorporated a lot of things into that.  I'm interested in kind of like how that physically happened too?  Did you write that out on your Selectrics and then send them the text...

        RP:	Selectric didn't appear in it.  I wrote it on the Atari.

        DB:	You wrote it on the Atari?  Okay.

        RP:	As I said for a good period, I was one of the few people in the country who was writing, everything I was writing to read off a screen on a computer, everything I was writing to read on paper on paper.  The Times asked me to review a book of prose by Philip Larkin.  I was having a little trouble getting started with it and I had been writing this very fluid Bubble World of computer.  I couldn't get started on the Larkin so I decided I'll experiment.  I'll see if I can write the lead on the computer, on that monochrome because it's so much less real than a pen or the typewriter.

        I wound up writing a draft of the whole fucking review on the Atari.  I can't print it out.  They were Dot Matrix printers over there at Synapse but I liked visiting Synapse anyway.  I did have, you may never have even seen one of these. I did have the 5.25-inch floppies.

        DB:	Oh yeah.

        RP:	That's why they are called floppies. T hose things were floppy, they were flexible.  So, I'm not sure if email was much used at the time.  I didn't email to Synapse.  I drove over to El Cerrito, into that office park where Synapse had its offices, right next to an old company named Pixel.

        [00:05:00]

        RP:	I used my 5.25-inch floppy to print out my book review and it dawned on me, "You have to get a printer.  In fact, you are going to have to get a better computer."

        So, within, I can't remember, probably a few weeks, I had a drooky, junkie Dot Matrix printer but we used to call a PC clone, IBM clone, called a Corona, I think was made in Italy oddly enough.  That was probably 1981, 1980, or something. It was quite early.

        DB:	You were already on your second computer by early ‘80s?

        RP:	The first one I owned and the second one I was using.

        DB:	Second one you were using. Just going back in the impetus for getting that first computer, was it from Synapse?

        RP:	They gave me the Atari.

        DB:	They gave you the Atari?

        RP:	Yeah.

        DB:	Okay. That's what I was trying to come.  When you were writing for them, would you...?

        RP:	It's all electronic.  The programmers would, they took their assembly language and the program they invented, William Mataga and later Cathryn Mataga.  William invented this program called BTZ, Better Than Zork. They were just putting to, this I remember, William was the sort of over programmer and the personal one, my partner was Steve Hales.  It says on the package of Mindwheel, "Mindwheel Electronic Novel by Robert Pinsky writer, William Mataga and Steve Hales programmers."

        The package is a hard cover book.  The product is just a floppy.  I remember my first conference with Steve.  He said, "I want you to describe your world to me," and then we had these interesting philosophical discussions of rooms and space, and scenes and time.  You think of the scene happening in a room, within the room happening in the scene.  There was an interesting conversation.

        DB:	You sort of the first...well...

        RP:	Dialogue tables and things like that...

        DB:	Really, conversation is about virtual space and... Yeah and coming out of some narrative and practice.  Can we move back a little bit?  Before all these, like when you were in your early writing career, would you say it's right around the time when you went to Stanford, when you sort of started writing?  I've read some of the interviews and some of the...

        RP:	Yeah. I thought of myself as a writer when I was at Rutgers as an undergraduate.  I was a beatnik want to be.  I was writing, I was writing poems.  I was editor of the undergraduate literary magazine.

        DB:	Oh cool.

        RP:	No.  I had a writing life.

        DB:	Okay, when you were starting off, what were your practices like?  Were you writing on, like did you keep notebooks?  Did you...?

        RP:	I have never kept notes.  I'm not a note maker.  I would get an idea for a poem, I would write it.  I remember for awhile I share an apartment with Alan Cheuse, novelist.  Those book reviews for NPR.  Alan is a year ahead of me and Alan is a fiction writer.  I could remember hearing his typewriter going. "tick, tick, tick."  I was sitting there, maybe with a paper and pen thinking, trying out different phrases in my mind and sort of ending that, "tick, tick, tick."

        DB:	Has it been since that time and throughout that kind of, you've always kind of felt it as a sort of voiced oral thing in your head before anything?

        RP:	I got more and more confident then, but yes that always was.  I felt that was my métier.  What I could do that I felt not everybody could do had to do with the sounds of sentences like that thing we just watched on TV.  The sounds of sentences where vowels and consonants work together, the way short sentences relates to a long sentence.

        DB:	How did you come to figure out that you could do that better than other people?

        [00:10:00]

        RP:	Probably in my course of college, but I could remember that as a kid, I would try to tap out the rhythm of senses with my fingers.  I thought about things like voiced and unvoiced consonants before I knew the word from them. I had been thinking about the difference between the ‘th' in "the" and the ‘th' in thin.  "The" you use your voice box, "thin" you don't.  I wasn't sure, it seems like a bad habit in a way...

        RP:	...but I thought about the sense of words.  So, it's not a surprise to me that I was good at it when I discovered there was an art based on such things.

        DB:	I guess the question is then how you kind of developed?  You had that sort of innate talent.  What were the steps you took to develop that talent?

        RP:	Reading.  I had great teachers.  My freshman year teacher Paul Fussell and he asked us to read ABC of Reading by Ezron Pound.  I read Yeats and Kingsburg and Bishop, and I recognized the way the sounds of words were doing things in those writers.  William Carlos Williams and William Butler Yeats and Emily Dickinson, I was less interested in the differences among them than the thing I saw going on in all of them.  I was interested by that thing.

        DB:	Yes.  That's such a better way to get into that.  So, I guess when you started to kind of compose the poems and they became more important to you personally but also important to your career and moving forward, what were the ways of you working on?  Were they always kind of appearing in your head, you'd write them down by hand and then type them up for other people.  What was the process there?

        RP:	I've had the ideas folding around the head for a long time, certain sense of ideas like humble things have histories.  What were the first things you ever saw made out of plastic in your own life?  Cheap shit from Japan after the war, toys mostly, plastic soldiers, metal soldiers during a war you couldn't get on, S.O.T.A. soldiers.  So I would thing about those substances.

        SPEAKER 1:	All set, everything is all set.

        RP:	I really appreciate it.  Thanks very  much.

        SPEAKER 1:	This is just all trash.  I'm just going to take this with me.

        RP:	You're taking my trash?

        SPEAKER 	I just don't want to leave it up here.

        RP:	Okay, I appreciate it.  Thanks a lot.  Those ideas, that set of ideas, they were by different materials, more about play, then I would think the word play.  That's all just thoughts.  At the same time, I'd be mixing up my own personal history and time, I listened to S.O.T.A. soldiers, Prestwood soldiers out overnight and they do mainly pull these all up and completely other set of ideas that might involve war and the fascination of war.

        I had an uncle who was in the Battle of The Bulge, he was a radio man and I remember being very tiny being vested by his massive boots.  He's wearing the boots and I'm on the road, touching those big boots.  That's the poem, that's memories, thoughts, ideas.  Then the poem is when you start putting some sounds together.  Something unnatural about the way the way a S.O.T.A. soldiers were in the rain, unlike the boots of my uncle when you started moving them.

        It's not an existing poem by the way.  I can give a little demo.  The poem starts when you start thinking about the vowels and consonants and with uncle, so you rearrange the consonants, unclean and calendar.  The calendar of hildhood, the time between the day that you find out wooden soldiers get run and the day that your mother and grandmother both dream that the dream was in trouble with Julian, negligent memories of unclean, blah, blah. That's the material.

        [00:15:00]

        DB:	Yes.  That's the material, yeah.  I guess the purpose of this interview is kind of to think about how that material becomes the book in all its iterations, and how that has changed over the course of as to how many computers do you think you have owned and how many different writing devices and stuff like that.  If you compose it in your head, will you have whole poems in your head before you write them down?

        RP:	Some poems, but more often I get enough lines to want to make a draft.  So I'll write them down and I'll look at those, recite to myself the different things I've written down and then I'll decide, type it into a document that you can print out, and then I'll read that over and maybe get a new idea.

        DB:	How was that?  What was that like in the early '70s, late '60s when you were...?

        RP:	Pre-computer?

        DB:	Yeah.

        RP:	Something came out of the typewriter that has a lot of bullet point all over it.

        DB:	Same sort of, you'd have a few lines you start to?

        RP:	Yeah.  Now it comes out of a laser printer and it has felt pen in all over it.

        DB:	Yeah.  When you are actually doing the writing down, you say you don't really usually use notebooks or anything. What is it you are writing on? Is it just bare paper or?

        RP:	Yeah.  My favorite kind of paper is very hard to get.  I'm forced to use this because it's very hard to get this.  I don't like the lines.

        DB:	Yeah, that's interesting.

        RP:	You get that somehow society doesn't take this very seriously anymore.  You can get a white, I don't want a white.

        DB:	You want a yellow?

        RP:	Yellow.

        DB:	I think that is the best color wise, yellow and black or some sort of yellow as the background is the best.

        RP:	Yellow and black, somehow a little more fluid than the black and white. So, in black and white it feels sort of legally reductive.

        DB:	Have you been working with blank yellow paper if you can, since early...?

        RP:	Yes.  We haven't talked much about prose.  I can remember working on prose and going through lots and lots of different processes, technologically, white out of course.  But I can remember before the IBM lift off, I could remember using the, they even made it double space, a sort of single space I believe, correction tape.  So, you could take a passage that you wanted to change and you glue the tape down and you might use a Xerox machine. You would do white out so the tape didn't leave a tell tale grey outline.  I can remember kind of thick palm set f pages where I had done that on some piece of prose.

        DB:	That would build up and build until you got it to where?

        RP:	I think early drafts of the situation of poetry, I was still at that stage of the tape and the white out and I'm probably forgetting a couple of other things I did to save having retype something.  Now I've met an editor who said he thinks prose declined, people started writing much more poorly when the computer made it so easy to do, insert passages that people rather than concentrating in editing and cutting and sculpting their prose, liked to insert that every sentence got a little bloated.

        DB:	In terms of that same process, how do you think that affected poetry and maybe yours specifically?

        RP:	I think poetry took an unproductive turn when people fell in love with the technology of the typewriter and [inaudible 00:33:44] very solemnly that had the new poet you count the spaces.  Proportional spacing came along within a decade or two and made nonsense of that.  To me, the graphic thing, people talk about lining things quite a lot.  I always feel, "No, I don't write line endings, I write lines" and it's the whole line.  I guess you could say I'm kind of an extremist and very resistant to the visual idea of the poem.

        Different technologies give people the illusion that poetry is a form of graphics and I guess for them it is.

        [00:20:00]

        RP:	For me, the unique quality of poetry is that it is vocal, it's on a human scale.  It comes out of one person's body, one syllable at a time.  There is not going to be anybody else around, I'm not talking about poetry readings or performance.  I'm talking about things very similar to the favorite poem project videos.  So, technology, the most important thing yet to be done and it's amazing to me it hasn't been done yet.

        Poetry, I was at Chancellor at the Academy of American Poets and they brought to us very proudly first chancellors to see somebody who had made a program, where the words of a poem can scroll and jump around. Team works do that on TV ads every day, it's they know; why don't they correct the fact that still, I think FSG won't publish poems in an electronic e-book edition because somehow nobody has come up with a way to preserve the integrity of the lines.  This means you can get a team of programmers to do that in a couple of days.

        DB:	I am also baffled by it.

        RP:	Probably going to happen by tomorrow but at the moment it's in this ridiculous stage where it hasn't happened, on the other hand, Harris didn't have visual lines.  They didn't make spaces between the words, they wanted to see if parchment or wax or papyrus or stone, whatever they were using.  So, you could figure out where the lines were because the rhythm was so strong.

        DB:	Strong, yeah.  For your own work then, you have a very strong sense and you are like Jimmy Michaels sort of too.  Have that strong sort of oral sense of poetry and are very dedicated to it. Did that come out of working with Winter or did that come out of kind of an innate sense of what you were doing from the beginning?

        RP:	I think there were some moment when I was reading Howell and [inaudible 00:37:15] and Dickinson, and I felt this reality in those things that was different from the reality of Alan's typewriter going staccato.  It was different from the reality of reading Ulysses or Double Learners.  That was a very powerful reality produced by those rectangular blocks of print and the pages.  This was more physical in some way, more boggly, let's say.

        So maybe made me ripe for Winters and he certainly amplified it by inviting me to learn something about George Gascoigne, Phillip Griffin, and Philip Sidne, Brohly, But I think it happened when I was in my late teens still and Gingsberg was obsessed by blank verse by Elliott and he gave himself these exercises in it.  So, it was as is Williams in a completely different way, it was free verse that was intensely oral.  William says all those poems called Metric Figure and then obviously Metric Figure is about their attempts to write intense rhythms that are not iambic or blank verse.

        DB:	Yeah and that move away from that.  It's such an interesting part of the century.  Let me get back to it, we've gone a little bit further than.  I guess the kind of overarching question that I'm wondering is and as a digital librarian and someone who is working in a digital new who has mostly, who can't really remember ever not writing on a computer or not using that.  When that computer came in, when the Atari came in and when the screens started appearing in front of you and the ease of those deletions and insertions and re-arrangements became possible, did that change the way you worked? Did that change what you produced?

        RP:	I don't think it changed what I produced but I think that it was the beginning of a different kind of archival anxiety.  There is the archival anxiety about people's works being preserved...

        [00:25:00]

        PR:	...given some manuscript or somebody else's manuscript being destroyed.  Over generation where I save magazines that I have worked in, that's the old anxiety and the new anxiety is the mortality of digital information.  I can remember the Librarian of Congress saying to me that the only way to preserve digital material is to reproduce it, unlike pirates, it's mortal.

        It turns to mush.  That aside from the fact that the medium keeps changing, the favor of poem project videos today I talked about somebody who is going to take the original digital tapes and make them into current high definition format rather than the flash format they are in.

        DB:	They are in flash?

        RP:	Yeah on the website, the website will be enhanced to be able to make them full screen.  For seven years I was in NewsHour with Jim Lehrer.  When Frank Sinatra died I read passages for Virgil about the death of the singer. When the stock market was in trouble, I read Frost's Provide, Provide.  At the time the places I recorded those would give me dumps on VHS tape.  Where are they?  Where is that material?  It's a lot of it.  I actually studied, this has gotten to the ether.  I was a portraiture of Slate for many years.  They eventually found poetry, it's not bringing up hits enough money and they add things.  They start doing it to preserve it for awhile.  There were years when I would do a poem out of copyright, classic poem, do a poem by Will You Marry and More.

        DB:	It's how I was introduced to Fowlerville.

        RP:	So I get those.  I was shocked to learn almost like everything, almost like all kind of pornography and ads and stuff, they are gone, the unretrievable.  Those discussions and so many are well known poets and critiques to placing and it's departing them, I vanished.

        DB:	What form were they written?

        RP:	They were in the fray, the discussion part that is I'm just responding to people.

        DB:	The comments actually below. Oh yeah.

        RP:	So, something quite valuable that I put effort into vanished.  We all vanish, we all die, and most objects are described and we don't know how long Shakespeare's reputation will last.  Here is the large view but there is also personal temporal anxiety.  One has mixed emotions when you know, my papers are at Stanford.  They bought up to a certain year of paper, papers and a librarian at Stanford said to me, "I hope you are saving your email.  I hope you are saving your electronic emails."  There is a new anxiety...

        [00:00:00] PART 3

        RP:	Maybe there. Within there that I wouldn't want loaded.

        DB:	Right, absolutely.

        RP:	Comes a journal.  So, there is the anxiety of what could be lost and the anxiety of what would be preserved you don't want preserved.  There is the anxiety of family levels on the metaphor for the whole thing.  The photographs, I share some photographs with my great grandparents' generation and these are photographs of your grandparents' generation that you treasure.  We are producing; we all have a camera in our pocket.  It shoots video.  Little tiny sliver has accesses almost all the information there is and you can create more forthright information with almost no effort at all.

        If you want your grand children to pay any attention to your family photos, you better edit them because the future generation doesn't want to spend all day listening to grandpa say, "Hi yeah!" You better think about what time capsule you create and as I say, that's only a metaphor for the larger question you are dealing with.  In one of my poems, my poem called, I think it's in my poem, The Forgetting.

        DB:	Which book is that in?

        RP:	In Gulf Music.

        DB:	In Gulf Music.

        RP:	I say, Ezra Pound praised the emperor, the emperor who appointed a committee of scholars to chose the advocate who has 1,000 best Noh dramas and destroy the others for the good of the Noh.  Ezra Pound approved of that, the fascist.  So I was trying to express ambivalence about the winnowing process and the selecting process.   The Library of Congress has to decide which sitcoms it will preserve, which commercials.  Some of those commercials and sitcoms maybe superior works of art to poetry by people who win the Pulitzer Prize.  Who decides?

        DB:	Librarians.

        RP:	I guess you do.

        DB:	I'm right here, talk to me.  What do you need?  In terms of that winnowing process then like what do you think about your own kind of, I'm sure you have uncollected works and stuff like that.  How do you feel towards those now and where do you store those?  Are they in paper, in certain boxes?  Are they in the papers in Stanford?

        RP:	The papers. I would store on, when I accumulate enough I shoot them off to Palerato.  Electronically, I mean, as it happens in the last few months, somebody, it happened twice, that a poem of mine that I didn't choose to put in the selected, one was personal, somebody said to me, "This poem of yours means a lot to me."  I remember the poem very well.  It's a poem called, I think it's called The Reasons.  This person said; it's a poem when I think about my ethnicity the way you deal with ethnicity, it's very important to me.  I felt maybe I shouldn't put in the selected and I didn't.

        [00:05:00]

        RP:	Then online, someone I have never met personally pointed to another poem because I published it in poetry magazine.  I was in my 20s.  It is on the poetry magazine website and she said how much she liked it.  I looked it up, I thought, "Pretty good."  I never put it in any book.  I had forgotten it entirely.  So, I don't know how that's drew me into your questions but it is to remain so.

        DB:	No. I think so.

        RP:	That there is no ultimate authority for that selection process, the author included.

        DB:	In terms of then, I'm trying to think how to segue this but it's probably not going to segue very well so I'll just ask.  You've created the poem.  Here is one way, you have these digital files that contain the poem and you've backed them up and you try to make sure that they are okay.  Do you feel some sort of, the word I have used here before is like "dearness towards them" or do you feel that they are sort of just a means to something else somewhere else?

        RP:	The word is mechanical, one is unreflecting.  I have many, many folders.  I'm sort of a quasi-organized person.  So, under documents in my hard drive which is then backed up in my backup drive under documents, you can tell on Pinsky home of the steps.  In my documents there are many, many folders, letters displaying with years, prose, probably 30, I haven't counted them.  There is one called drafts.  In drafts under sub-folders for most poems there is that DR1, DR12, DR14.  I look at it and I sometimes feel the way I have told you I feel about the family photographs.  Nobody wants all this.  Bishop has a crucial say about the umbrella that was so hard to make and the leather trousers, gave them to the local museum.  How can anybody want such things?  I'm sure she's thinking about drafts and memorabilia and so forth.  It's just another anxiety.  I can't say I think about it a lot but I'm ambivalent when I think about all those megabytes of drafts and two separate questions are, do I want anyone to look at them and who could possibly want to look at them?  But I don't destroy them and I do somewhat mechanically shoot a dress with a dress.  I guess part of the theory is I might want to look and I suppose once in many, many months I do look.

        DB:	So, you are saving each poem as a new draft?  It's not like one poem with many drafts in it.  It's just each poem a new file, a new draft?

        RP:	A new folder.  No, each poem for a poem.  Let's say the poem is called The Mechanical Pencil.  Then I'll have a name like Mech Pencil and with an upper case M and P.

        [00:10:00]

        RP:	You have Mech Pencil DR1.x or Mech Pencil DR6.ocx, Mech Pencil 47 and maybe not every single one is saved and they are all going to that folder.  In the main file, which is the next book, book.pm, whatever that folder you have the separate poems.

        DB:	Have you been doing that your whole...?  When did you start using this sort of folder system?

        RP:	I can't remember when I started doing it.

        DB:	But it's been pretty consistent.

        RP:	But probably since I started using a computer.

        DB:	Yeah. Do you feel like you kind of envision the poems in that way, like when you are kind of like thinking about them later does that ever pop into your mind?

        RP:	When I think about the poem I think about it in my book or as part of my poetry reading, or if I'm in a particularly grandiose and hopeful state, I picture somebody reading it the way that people in the favorite poem project, the way Cefaloni reads plants, like in the candlestick.

        DB:	Yeah.  I was watching the South Boston...

        RP:	Oh the kid.

        DB:	John.

        RP:	John Ulrich

        DB:	Yeah. John Ulrich.

        RP:	John meets Gwendolyn Brooks, so "We Real Cool."

        DB:	I was struck by how much I wanted to know how he's doing.  I was interested in him, the poem is great and everything but it just made me like...

        RP:	The last I heard he was doing okay.

        DB:	I hope so. Good.   I guess I'm a little unclear as to how, like what your revision process is like.  I think I have a sense of how the compositions happen and then when you have, say, most of the poem ready, like when you are moving from drafts 020 to 021.  What are you doing in between there?

        RP:	Print out, right on the printout.

        DB:	Are you reading it out loud.

        RP:	See if you have the poem by memory.  I might turn the light off going to sleep, try to recite the poem if you come to a part you don't have maybe that's the part you need to work on.  Not reliably, but sometimes.

        DB:	Do you have like an intention in doing that?  Is each poem different or is there?

        RP:	Yeah.  The intention is to make it worth somebody getting by heart or wanting to read to their friend or wanting to recite to themselves on a hike or when they are driving.  Do whatever it is that poems do.

        DB:	So, kind of realize that the poem is... What happens when a poem doesn't realize that?  How do you know that a poem is not going to get there?

        RP:	In my case, you keep working and very rarely you abandon it, usually some parts of it that's worth it gets incorporated to the next poem or to some future poems.

        DB:	So, you kind of take parts and...

        RP:	Yes.  You use it like the way Cubans do parts of sugar lace.

        DB:	Okay.  Do other people have work in this?  Do other people kind of mentor into this process?

        RP:	Yeah. I have friends, Louise sees what I write, Alan sees what I write and maybe Gail Mazur.  Different times of my life there have been different friends, always somebody around.  Jim Olson sometimes I email things to to Jim.

        DB:	At what stage do the people usually come in?

        RP:	Fairly late.

        DB:	Fairly late?

        RP:	Yeah.

        DB:	To kind of get a reaction and something like that.  Was the translation work and using the computer any sort of processes, was it fundamentally different or what?  Did it share a similar..?

        RP:	It was rather similar. Felt pen and I would print it in the Atari and a trod, whatever, I can't tell was working on. So, two or three pieces of paper, maybe one piece of paper.  I had everything I needed and then it was the metrical game.

        DB:	You described that in I think one of the interviews I've read, I sort of like just intensely pleasurable sort of work.  What kept you drawing you back to it?

        RP:	It's why kids play video games.  It's why guys play golf.  It's a difficulty that you become addicted to. You become entranced by the difficulty.  People need to do the New York Times Crossword puzzle every day.  It's that part of the mind, the part of the mind that loves to solve difficulties. Or let's not say solve, engage a certain kind of difficulty because the video games offer infinite, you can't ever solve it.  You can get better at it.

        RP:	And making those tursets, those consonantal rhyme tursets and pentameters and always compressing.  I use fewer words in that translation than any other translation, prose or verse.  Always never pay it to get a rhyme, compress to get a rhyme.  That was the rule and that became what a jigsaw puzzle is for somebody who loves jigsaw puzzles, what a video game is for somebody who loves video games became absorbing.

        DB:	How long did that project last?

        RP:	It was a year to get through the inferno ones and almost another year to revise.

        DB:	I read about and then you worked on a revision with Frank Bidart, some of it too?

        RP:	Yes. We put a lot of effort into that.

        DB:	Yeah.  So, you have like the individual poems that you work on and then... How does these poems then for you, how do you get them into a book?

        RP:	There is a sub-folder in the... There is a folder called book.pms and it acquires a name and the book acquires a title but it's the next book of poems.  In that folder right now there is a file called, I think, it's book29. That is the 29th draft and I bothered to have a contents page, which Nisus Writer does very well.  A contents page, page numbers, and an order of the poems they are in.  That order will change but what I have with me if I go somewhere to give a poetry reading and it's a file, it's a folder.

        DB:	How do you construct your orders?

        RP:	I guess it's different for each book.  I'm not sure how to answer, I just see as your pants.  It's intuitive.

        [00:15:00]

        DB:	Does it have some sort of phrasing to it?  Is it musical in that sense?

        RP:	Ideas and feelings get introduced.  I hope then they get developed and amplified and explained, and then I hope new elements come in, in the course of that process.  At the same time one recognizes that a good number of readers don't read the poems in order, some people like to start in the middle, some people start at the end, but for those who want to see something in the order, Gulf Music starts with a kind of peculiar title poem.  It says this is not going to be easy and it's going to involve the newspaper and it's not going to take certain conventional routes for political poetry.

        DB:	I found the ordering and construction of Gulf Music to be very unusual. I was just sort of thinking about it being just unlike most things that come out now.

        RP:	I thought about it a lot, I did want to make it something distinctive and it starts with the most guzzle like thing in the book.

        DB:	Yeah.  Are you on draft 129 of the current book?

        RP:	Yes.

        DB:	Is that where you are at?

        RP:	Yes.

        DB:	Do you have any idea when that... That's just for me but do you know when you..?

        RP:	I'm on leave next year.  I hope that before the year is over, I'll have the book.

        DB:	How has teaching influenced the way you write?  Has it done much or has it sort of being the way that you support the time that you get to do the writing?

        RP:	It's not an easy question to answer.  I'm proud of and as a profession it's an honorable profession, and I think I have probably helped more people than I've hurt people, and I still seemed to be getting something out of what I do as a teacher.  I guess they help, I ask them to make anthologies.  So, I guess among other things, they help me have a sense of what is currently esteemed.  Change has a frightening morbidity that every two or three years the calendar is very different.

        DB:	Has that rate increased in more recent years, now that the internet has kind of made things more available?

        RP:	It could be or it could be just as I get older, I'm more disturbed by it or delighted by it or something.  But it certainly does suggest that the wheel of fashion spins along pretty well.

        DB:	I guess there are other questions about kind of the correspondence and I know you talked about the anxiety of saving emails and stuff like that.  Were you a big physical letter writing centered?

        RP:	I used to write a lot of letters.  There used to be a way I would warm up.  I remember when I was working on the situation of poetry, I would warm up. I had a routine where first I'd write a letter or two, maybe three, and that would somehow make me feel I was working than to glide into working on a poem or in that prose project.  It was somehow made easier and I used to get a lot of letters and I used to send a lot of letters.  I still do once in awhile but electronic has taken over.

        DB:	Can you point to a time when that sort of wave over took?

        RP:	I think in the late '80s or early '90s. People you think would never adapt to email adapted to email.  It became more and more of a Lingua Franca, I think people had become; became the agora.  It became where people met and the generation that only did paper correspondence, got old and died, to be blunt about it.

        DB:	Do you find that it is a different genre?  Do you find that there is like interest, different...?

        RP:	Different conventions.

        DB:	Yeah.

        RP:	I must say that when I see letters I wrote long ago I wince, I don't like it.

        DB:	Why not?

        RP:	It's either naivety or there is falseness or there is clumsiness.  To write a good letter in a way you have to not think about how...

        [00:20:00]

        RP:	...you are sounding or looking.  It should be ephemeral, it should be at the moment and then to have it preserved for 20 years, it's a little disturbing.

        DB:	Do you think that there is more of an awareness of that with email, like more of like a...?

        RP:	I think email is probably more unconscious.  I was joking with you about my friend who says scandalous things in emails, I repeatedly tell him, "Look out!"  Things you read in newspaper, some business setting or political setting people get nailed the email trail.  It maybe generationally something is changing.  I think people say things in email they wouldn't say, "in writing" because they don't think of it as having as much permanence and sometimes it surprises them.

        DB:	I think it's very prominent for you.  My first job out of college as a paralegal I just looked through email after emails for Hot Docs as I was told.

        RP:	And hitting delete...

        DB:	It doesn't do it. No it doesn't.

        RP:	It doesn't shred it.

        DB:	No. So, kind of more overall, do you think the advent of the kind of computer and the rise of the computer in your sort of practice has changed things fundamentally?  What if the computer had never really...?  What if you were still working with your IBM Selectric?

        RP:	Publication is different.  We've been talking about production and production has changed somewhat for me, probably not as much as many people, probably because I have been doing it so long with a computer and because poetry for me is vocal.  Publication is in a midst of some kind of tremendous transition.  I don't think anybody knows where it's going exactly.  I recently spent a few days in New York.  It's pleasing to see the people with a book in the subway, a magazine or a newspaper, but most people who are looking at something at looking at the screen.  I'm surprised how many are looking at tablets.  Lots are looking at phones and a certain number are playing games, a certain number are checking their email, a certain number are listening to music and looking at something that goes with the music.  How many are reading?  I don't know.  But at the moment if a magazine tells you they want to put something in their web page rather than print, you feel the second level of affection for this, that maybe shifting.

        DB:	Yeah. I wonder about that too. I feel like it's right on that cusp.

        RP:	I think it's all very fluent and we don't know and I don't think anybody really is quite sure what's going to happen next. I guess one has to not think about it too much.

        DB:	Yeah.  You have to make those decisions.  Your point about the formatting and about them not figuring that out yet...

        RP:	That's going to happen soon.

        DB:	Yeah. But I mean even in HTML, even if you see your poems get put up there, there is so many, I just see so many like prob... Just easy problems that people just don't know because there are so many different levels of expertise.

        RP:	It used to drive me crazy on Slate when an ad would disrupt a poem.

        DB:	Yeah.  Like the break the line in a weird way or something like that, maybe a famous poem.  Yeah.

        RP:	Are we almost done?

        DB:	Yes.

        RP:	I'm getting a little worn out.

        DB:	I think we are done.

        RP:	Good.

        DB:	Okay. Thank you very much Robert.

        RP:	It's great and it was fun, a smart thing to get into.

        DB:	We'll see.

        [end of audio 24:35]

        

    </transcript><rights>Copyright Devin Becker, all rights reserved.
    </rights><fmt/><usage/><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation/><xmlfilename>pinsky.xml</xmlfilename><collection_link> http://www.devinbecker.org/ctrl-shift/</collection_link><series_link/></record>
</ROOT>
